<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tales>
    <story>
        <title>THE FOX AS HERDSMAN</title>
        <body>
            <p>Once on a time there was a <character who="woman">woman</character> who went out to hire
                a herdsman, and she met a <character who="bear">bear</character>.</p>
            <p><fig_lang type="personification" subject="bear">“Whither away, Goody?” said <character
                who="bear">Bruin</character></fig_lang>.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="bear">“Oh, I’m going out to hire a herdsman”,
                answered the <character who="woman">woman</character>.</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="bear" subject="woman"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="bear"
                >“Why not have me for a herdsman?” said <character who="bear"
                    >Bruin</character>.</fig_lang></dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="bear">“Well, why not?” said the <character
                who="woman">woman</character>. “If you only knew how to call the flock; just let
                me hear?”</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="bear" subject="woman">“OW, OW!” growled the <character who="bear">bear</character>.</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="bear">“No, no! I won’t have you”, said the <character who="woman">woman</character>,</dialogue> as
                soon as she heard him say that, and off she went on her way.
            </p>
            <p>So, when she had gone a bit further, she met a <character who="wolf">wolf</character>.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="wolf" subject="woman"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="wolf"
                >“Whither away, Goody?” asked the <character who="wolf">Wolf</character>.</fig_lang></dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="wolf">“Oh!” said she, “I’m going out to hire a
                herdsman.”</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="wolf" subject="woman"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="wolf"
                >“Why not have me for a herdsman?” said the Wolf.</fig_lang></dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="wolf">“Well, why not? if you can only call the flock;
                let me hear?” said she.</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="wolf" subject="woman">“UH, UH!” said the <character who="wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="wolf">“No, no!” said the <character who="woman">woman</character>; “you’ll never do for
                me.”</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p>Well, after she had gone a while longer, she met a <character who="fox">fox</character>.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="fox" subject="woman"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="fox"
                >“Whither away, Goody?” asked the <character who="fox">Fox</character>.</fig_lang></dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="fox">“Oh, I’m just going out to hire a herdsman”, said
                the <character who="woman">woman</character>.</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="fox" subject="woman"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="fox"
                >“Why not have me for your herdsman?” asked the <character who="fox">Fox</character>.</fig_lang></dialogue>
            </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="fox">“Well, why not?” said she; “if you only knew how
                to call the flock; let me hear?”</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="fox" subject="woman">“DIL-DAL-HOLOM”, sung out the <character who="fox">Fox</character>, in such a fine
                clear voice.</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="woman" subject="fox">“Yes; I’ll have you for my herdsman”, said the
                woman; and so she set the Fox to herd her flock.</dialogue></p>
            <p>The first day the <character who="fox">Fox</character> was herdsman he <action actor="fox" subject="woman" sign="negative"
                >ate up all the woman’s goats; the next day he made an end of all her sheep; and the
                third day he ate up all her kine.</action> So, when he came home at even, the woman
                asked what he had done with all her flocks?</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="fox" subject="woman"><fig_lang type="pesonification" subject="fox"
                >“Oh!” said the <character who="fox">Fox</character>, “their skulls are in the stream, and their bodies in the
                holt.”</fig_lang></dialogue>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <character who="woman">the Goody</character> stood and churned when the fox said this, but she thought she might as
                well step out and see after her flock; and while she was away <action actor="fox"
                    subject="cream" sign="negative">the Fox crept into the churn and ate up the
                    cream.</action> So when the Goody came back and saw that, she fell into such a rage,
                that <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="fox" sign="negative"><action
                    actor="woman" subject="fox" sign="negative">she snatched up the little morsel of
                    the cream that was left, and threw it at the fox as he ran off,</action> so that
                    he got a dab of it on the end of his tail, and that’s the reason why the fox has a
                    white tip to his brush.</descriptor></p>
        </body>
    </story>
    <story>
    <title>THE GIANT WHO HAD NO HEART IN HIS BODY</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time there was a <character who="King">king</character>
            <descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="King" sign="neutral">who had seven sons, and he
                loved them so much that he could never bear to be without them all at once, but one
                must always be with him.</descriptor> Now, when they were grown up, <character
                who="Princes">six</character> were to set off to woo, but as for the <descriptor
                speaker="Narrator" subject="Boots" sign="neutral">youngest</descriptor>, his father
            kept him at home, and the others were to bring back a princess for him to the palace.
                <action actor="King" subject="princes" sign="positive">So the king gave the six the
                finest clothes you ever set eyes on, so fine that the light gleamed from them a long
                way off, and each had his horse, which cost many, many hundred dollars, and so they
                set off.</action><descriptor subject="princes" sign="neutral" speaker="Narrator">
                Now, when they had been to many palaces, and seen many princesses, at last they came
                to a king who had <character who="princesses">six daughters</character>; such lovely
                king’s daughters they had never seen, and so they fell to wooing them, each one, and
                when they had got them for sweethearts, they set off home again</descriptor>,
                <action subject="Boots" sign="negative" actor="princes">but they quite forgot that
                they were to bring back with them a sweetheart for <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character>, their brother, who stayed at home, for they were over head
                and ears in love with their own sweethearts.</action></p>
        <p>But when they had gone a good bit on their way, they passed close by a steep hill-side,
            like a wall, where the giant’s house was, and there the <character who="Giant"
                >giant</character> came out, and set his eyes upon them, and <action actor="Giant"
                subject="princes and princesses" sign="negative">turned them all into stone, princes
                and princesses and all.</action>
            <descriptor subject="King" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">Now the king waited and
                waited for his six sons, but the more he waited, the longer they stayed away; so he
                fell into great trouble, and said he should never know what it was to be glad
                again.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="King" subject="Boots">“And if I had not you left”, he said to
                    <character who="Boots">Boots</character>, “I would live no longer, so full of
                sorrow am I for the loss of your brothers.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="King">“Well, but now I’ve been thinking to ask your
                leave to set out and find them again; that’s what I’m thinking of”, said <character
                    who="Boots">Boots</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="King" subject="Boots">“Nay, nay!” said his father; “that leave you
                shall never get, for then you would stay away too.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>But <character who="Boots">Boots</character> had set his heart upon it; go he would; and
            he begged and prayed so long that the <character who="King">king</character> was forced
            to let him go. <descriptor subject="King" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">Now, you
                must know the king had no other horse to give <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> but an old broken-down jade, for his six other sons and their
                train had carried off all his horses;</descriptor> but <character who="Boots"
                >Boots</character> did not care a pin for that, he sprang up on his
            sorry-old-steed.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="King">“Farewell, father”, said he; “I’ll come back,
                never fear, and like enough I shall bring my six brothers back with me”; and with
                that he rode off.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So, when he had ridden a while, he came to a <character who="Raven">Raven</character>,
                <descriptor subject="Raven" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">which lay in the road
                and flapped its wings, and was not able to get out of the way, it was so
                starved.</descriptor></p>
        <p><fig_lang type="personification" subject="Raven">“Oh, dear friend”, said the <character
                    who="Raven">Raven</character>, “give me a little food, and I’ll help you again
                at your utmost need.”</fig_lang>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Raven">“I haven’t much food”, said the <character
                    who="Boots">Prince</character>, “and I don’t see how you’ll ever be able to help
                me much; but still I can spare you a little. I see you want it.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Boots" subject="Raven" sign="positive">So he gave the <character
                    who="Raven">raven</character> some of the food he had brought with him.</action>
        </p>
        <p>Now, when he had gone a bit further, he came to a brook, and in the brook lay a
                <character who="Salmon">great Salmon</character>, <descriptor subject="Salmon"
                sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">which had got upon a dry place and dashed itself
                about, and could not get into the water again.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Salmon" subject="Boots"><fig_lang type="personification"
                    subject="Salmon">“Oh, dear friend”, said the <character who="Salmon"
                        >Salmon</character> to the <character who="Boots">Prince</character>; “shove
                    me out into the water again, and I’ll help you again at your utmost
                    need.”</fig_lang></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Salmon">“Well!” said the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character>, “the help you’ll give me will not be great, I daresay, but
                it’s a pity you should lie there and choke”</dialogue>; and with that <action
                actor="Boots" subject="Salmon" sign="positive">he shot the fish out into the stream
                again.</action></p>
        <p>After that he went a long, long way, and there met him a <character who="Wolf"
                >Wolf</character>, which was so famished that it lay and crawled along the road on
            its belly.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="Wolf"
                    >“Dear friend, do let me have your horse”, said the <character who="Wolf"
                        >Wolf</character>; “I’m so hungry the wind whistles through my ribs; I’ve
                    had nothing to eat these two years.”</fig_lang></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Wolf">“No”, said <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character>, “this will never do; “first I came to a <character
                    who="Raven">raven</character>, and I was forced to give him my food; next I came
                to a <character who="Salmon">salmon</character>, and him I had to help into the
                water again; and now you will have my horse. It can’t be done, that it can’t, for
                then I should have nothing to ride on.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Nay, dear friend, but you can help me”, said
                    <character who="Wolf">Graylegs the wolf</character>; “you can ride upon my back,
                and I’ll help you again in your utmost need.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Well! the help I shall get from you will not
                be great, I’ll be bound”, said the <character who="Boots">Prince</character>; “but
                you may take my horse, since you are in such need.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Wolf" subject="Boots" sign="postive">So when the <character who="Wolf"
                    >wolf</character> had eaten the horse, <character who="Boots">Boots</character>
                took the bit and put it into the wolf’s jaw, and laid the saddle on his back;
                    <descriptor subject="Wolf" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">and now the
                        <character who="Wolf">wolf</character> was so strong, after what he had got
                    inside, that he set off with the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> like
                    nothing. So fast he had never ridden before.</descriptor></action>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“When we have gone a bit farther”, <character
                    who="Wolf">said Graylegs</character>; “I’ll show you the Giant’s
                house.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So after a while they came to it.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots"><descriptor subject="Giant's House"
                    sign="negative" speaker="Wolf">“See, here is the Giant’s house”, said the
                        <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>; “and see, here are your six
                    brothers, whom the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> has turned into
                    stone; and see here are their six brides, and away yonder is the door, and in at
                    that door you must go.”</descriptor></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Wolf">“Nay, but I daren’t go in”, said the <character
                    who="Boots">Prince</character>; “he’ll take my life.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“No! no!” said the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character>; “when you get in you’ll find a Princess, and she’ll tell you
                what to do to make an end of the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>. Only mind
                and do as she bids you.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Well! <character who="Boots">Boots</character> went in, but, truth to say, he was very
            much afraid. When he came in the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> was away, but
            in one of the rooms sat the <character who="Princess">Princess</character>, just as the
                <character who="Wolf">wolf</character> had said, <descriptor speaker="Boots"
                subject="Princess" sign="positive">and so lovely a princess <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> had never yet set eyes on.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Oh! heaven help you! whence have you
                come?” said the <character who="Princess">Princess</character>, as she saw him; “it
                will surely be your death. No one can make an end of the Giant who lives here, for
                he has no heart in his body.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“Well! well!” said <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character>; “but now that I am here, I may as well try what I can do
                with him; and I will see if I can’t free my brothers, who are standing turned to
                stone out of doors; and you, too, I will try to save, that I will.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Well, if you must, you must”, said the
                    <character who="Princess">Princess</character>; “and so let us see if we can’t
                hit on a plan. Just creep under the bed yonder, and mind and listen to what he and I
                talk about. But, pray, do lie as still as a mouse.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Boots" subject="bed" sign="neutral">So he crept under the bed, and he had
                scarce got well underneath it,</action> before the <character who="Giant"
                >Giant</character> came.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Ha!” roared the <character who="Giant"
                    >Giant</character>, “what a smell of Christian blood there is in the
                house!”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Yes, I know there is”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>, “for there came a magpie flying with a
                man’s bone, and let it fall down the chimney. I made all the haste I could to get it
                out, but all one can do, the smell doesn’t go off so soon.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> said no more about it, and when night
            came, they went to bed. After they had lain awhile, the <character who="Princess"
                >Princess</character> said:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“There is one thing I’d be so glad to ask
                you about, if I only dared.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“What thing is that?” asked the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Only where it is you keep your heart,
                since you don’t carry it about you”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Ah! that’s a thing you’ve no business to
                ask about; but if you must know, it lies under the door-sill”, said the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Boots">“Ho! ho!” said <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> to himself under the bed, “then we’ll soon see if we can’t
                find it.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Next morning the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> got up cruelly early, and
            strode off to the wood; but he was hardly out of the house before <action
                actor="Boots and Princess" subject="Giant's heart" sign="neutral"><character
                    who="Boots">Boots</character> and the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character> set to work to look under the door-sill for his heart; but
                the more they dug, and the more they hunted, the more they couldn’t find
                it.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“He has baulked us this time”, said the
                    <character who="Princess">Princess</character>, “but we’ll try him once
                more.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Princess" subject="flowers" sign="positive">So she picked all the
                prettiest flowers she could find, and strewed them over the door-sill, which they
                had laid in its right place again</action>; and when the time came for the
                <character who="Giant">Giant</character> to come home again,<action actor="Boots"
                subject="bed" sign="neutral">
                <character who="Boots">Boots</character> crept under the bed.</action> Just as he
            was well under, back came the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</p>
        <p>Snuff—snuff, went the Giant’s nose. <dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“My eyes
                and limbs, what a smell of Christian blood there is in here”, said
            he.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“I know there is”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>, “for there came a magpie flying with a
                man’s bone in his bill, and let it fall down the chimney. I made as much haste as I
                could to get it out, but I daresay it’s that you smell.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> held his peace, and said no more about
            it. A little while after, he asked who it was that had strewed flowers about the
            door-sill.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Oh, I, of course”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“And, pray, what’s the meaning of all
                this?” said the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Ah!” said the Princess, “I’m so fond of
                you that I couldn’t help strewing them, when I knew that your heart lay under
                there.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“You don’t say so”, said the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>; “but after all it doesn’t lie there at
                all.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So when they went to bed again in the evening, the <character who="Princess"
                >Princess</character> asked the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> again where
            his heart was, for she said she would so like to know.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Well”, said the <character who="Giant"
                    >Giant</character>, “if you must know, it lies away yonder in the cupboard
                against the wall.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots and Princess" subject="themselves">“So, so!” thought <character
                    who="Boots">Boots</character> and the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>; “then we’ll soon try to find it.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Next morning the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> was away early, and strode off
            to the wood, and so soon as he was gone <action actor="Boots and Princess"
                subject="Giant's heart" sign="neutral"><character who="Boots">Boots</character> and
                the <character who="Princess">Princess</character> were in the cupboard hunting for
                his heart, but the more they sought for it, the less they found it.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Well”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>, “we’ll just try him once more.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Princess" subject="decorating cupboard" sign="positive">So she decked out
                the cupboard with flowers and garlands, and when the time came for the Giant to come
                home, <action actor="Boots" subject="bed" sign="neutral"><character who="Boots"
                        >Boots</character> crept under the bed again.</action></action>
        </p>
        <p>Then back came the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</p>
        <p>Snuff-snuff! <dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“My eyes and limbs, what a
                smell of Christian blood there is in here!”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“I know there is”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>; “for a little while since there came a
                magpie flying with a man’s bone in his bill, and let it fall down the chimney. I
                made all the haste I could to get it out of the house again; but after all my pains,
                I daresay it’s that you smell.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>When the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> heard that, he said no more about it;
            but a little while after, he saw how the cupboard was all decked about with flowers and
            garlands; so he asked who it was that had done that? Who could it be but the <character
                who="Princess">Princess</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“And, pray, what’s the meaning of all this
                tom-foolery?” asked the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Oh, I’m so fond of you, I couldn’t help
                doing it when I knew that your heart lay there”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“How can you be so silly as to believe any
                such thing?” said the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Oh yes; how can I help believing it, when
                you say it”, said the <character who="Princess">Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“You’re a goose”, said the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>; “where my heart is, you will never
                come.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Well”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>;” but for all that, ’twould be such a pleasure to know
                where it really lies.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Then the poor <character who="Giant">Giant</character> could hold out no longer, but was
            forced to say:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Far, far away in a lake lies an island; on
                that island stands a church; in that church is a well; in that well swims a duck; in
                that duck there is an egg, and in that egg there lies my heart,—you
                darling!”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>In the morning early, while it was still grey dawn, the <character who="Giant"
                >Giant</character> strode off to the wood.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Yes! now I must set off too”, said
                    <character who="Boots">Boots</character>; “if I only knew how to find the
                way.”</dialogue> He took a long, long farewell of the <character who="Princess"
                >Princess</character>, <action actor="Wolf" subject="Boots" sign="positive">and when
                he got out of the Giant’s door, there stood the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character> waiting for him. So <character who="Boots">Boots</character>
                told him all that had happened inside the house, and said now he wished to ride to
                the well in the church, if he only knew the way. So the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character> bade him jump on his back, he’d soon find the way; and away
                they went, till the wind whistled after them, over hedge and field, over hill and
                dale. After they had travelled many, many days, they came at last to the lake. Then
                the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> did not know how to get over it, but
                the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character> bade him only not be afraid, but stick
                on, and so he jumped into the lake with the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> on his back, and swam over to the island. So they came to
                the church</action>; <descriptor subject="key" sign="negative" speaker="Boots"/>but
            the church keys hung high, high up on the top of the tower, and at first the <character
                who="Boots">Prince</character> did not know how to get them down.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“You must call on the <character who="Raven"
                    >raven</character>”, said the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Raven" subject="Boots" sign="positive">So the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> called on the <character who="Raven">raven</character>, and
                in a trice the <character who="Raven">raven</character> came, and flew up and
                fetched the keys, and so the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> got into the
                church</action>. But when he came to the well, there lay the duck, and swam about
            backwards and forwards, just as the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> had said.
                <action actor="Boots" subject="egg" sign="negative">So the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> stood and coaxed it and coaxed it, till it came to him, and
                he grasped it in his hand; but just as he lifted it up from the water the duck
                dropped the egg into the well, and then <character who="Boots">Boots</character> was
                beside himself to know how to get it out again.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Well, now you must call on the <character
                    who="Salmon">salmon</character> to be sure”, said the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character></dialogue>; and the <character who="Boots">king’s
                son</character> called on the <character who="Salmon">salmon</character>, <action
                actor="Salmon" subject="Boots" sign="positive">and the <character who="Salmon"
                    >salmon</character> came and fetched up the egg from the bottom of the
                well.</action></p>
        <p>Then the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character> told him to <action actor="Boots"
                subject="Giant" sign="positive">squeeze the egg, and as soon as ever he squeezed it
                the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> screamed out.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Squeeze it again”, said the <character
                    who="Wolf">Wolf</character></dialogue>; <action actor="Boots" subject="Giant"
                sign="positive">and when the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> did so, the
                    <character who="Giant">Giant</character> screamed still more piteously,</action>
            and <descriptor speaker="Giant" subject="Boots" sign="neutral">begged and prayed so
                prettily to be spared, saying he would do all that the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> wished if he would only not squeeze his heart in
                two.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Tell him, if he will restore to life again your
                six brothers and their brides, whom he has turned to stone, you will spare his
                life”, said the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue> Yes, the
                <character who="Giant">Giant</character> was ready to do that, and <action
                actor="Giant" subject="princes and princesses" sign="positive">he turned the six
                brothers into king’s sons again, and their brides into king’s
            daughters.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Now, squeeze the egg in two”, said the
                    <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue>
            <action actor="Boots" subject="Giant" sign="positive"> So <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> squeezed the egg to pieces, <descriptor subject="Giant"
                    sign="positive" speaker="narrator">and the <character who="Giant"
                        >Giant</character> burst at once.</descriptor></action>
        </p>
        <p>Now, when he had made an end of the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>, <descriptor
                subject="Boots, Princess, princes, and princess" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator"
                    ><character who="Boots">Boots</character> rode back again on the <character
                    who="Wolf">wolf</character> to the Giant’s house, and there stood all his six
                brothers alive and merry, with their brides. Then <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> went into the hill-side after his bride, and so they all set
                off home again to their father’s house.</descriptor>
            <descriptor subject="King" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">And you may fancy how glad
                the old king was when he saw all his seven sons come back, each with his
                bride—</descriptor><dialogue speaker="King" subject="everyone"><descriptor
                    subject="Princess" sign="positive" speaker="King">“But the loveliest bride of
                    all is the <character who="Princess">bride of Boots</character>, after all”,
                    said the <character who="King">king</character>,</descriptor><descriptor
                    subject="Boots" sign="positive" speaker="King"> “and he shall sit uppermost at
                    the table, with her by his side.”</descriptor></dialogue></p>
        <p><action actor="King" subject="wedding" sign="positive"/>So he sent out, and called a
            great wedding-feast, and the mirth was both loud and long, and if they have not done
            feasting, why, they are still at it.</p>
    </body>
</story>
    <story>
        <title>TAMING THE SHREW</title>
        <body>
            <p>Once on a time there was a <character>king</character>, and he had a
                <character>daughter</character> who was such <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                    subject="Princess" sign="negative">a scold</descriptor>, and whose<fig_lang
                        type="personification" subject="Princess" sign="negative"> tongue went so fast,
                        there was no stopping it</fig_lang>. So he gave out that the man who could stop her
                tongue should have the Princess to wife, and half his kingdom into the bargain. Now,
                three brothers, who heard this, made up their minds to go and try their luck; and first
                of all the two elder went, for they thought they were the cleverest; but they couldn’t
                cope with her at all, and got well thrashed besides.</p>
            <p> Then <character>Boots</character>, the <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Boots" sign="neutral">
                youngest</descriptor>, set off, and when he had gone a little way he found an ozier
                band lying on the road, and he picked it up. When he had gone a little farther he found
                a piece of a broken plate, and he picked that up too. A little farther on he found a
                dead magpie, and a little farther on still, a crooked ram’s horn; so he went on a bit
                and found the fellow to the horn; and at last, just as he was crossing the fields by the
                king’s palace, where they were pitching out dung, he found a worn-out shoe-sole. All
                these things he took with him into the palace, and went before the Princess.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots"> “Good day”</dialogue>, said he.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">
                “Good day”</dialogue>, said she, and made a wry face.</p> 
            <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Can I get my magpie cooked here?”</dialogue> he asked.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“I’m afraid it will burst”</dialogue>,answered the Princess.</p>
            <p> <dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Oh! never fear! for I’ll just tie this ozier band round it”</dialogue>,
                said the lad, as he pulled it out.</p>
            <p> <dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“The fat will run out of it”</dialogue>, said the Princess.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Then I’ll hold this under it”</dialogue>, said the lad, and showed her the piece of broken plate.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“You are so <descriptor speaker="Princess" subject="Boots" sign="negative">crooked</descriptor> in your words”</dialogue>
                , said the Princess, <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“there’s no knowing where to have you.”</dialogue></p>
            <p> <dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“No, I’m not crooked”</dialogue>, said the lad; <dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">
                “but this is”</dialogue>, as he held up one of the horns.</p>
            <p> <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Well!”</dialogue> said the Princess, <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“I never saw the match of this in all my days.”</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“Why here you see the match to it”</dialogue>, said the lad, as he pulled out the other ram’s horn.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“I think”</dialogue>, said the Princess, <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“you must have come here to wear out my tongue with your
                nonsense.”</dialogue></p> 
            <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“No, I have not”</dialogue>, said the lad; <dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“but this is worn out”</dialogue>, as he pulled out the
                shoe-sole. To this the Princess hadn’t a word to say, for she had fairly lost her voice
                with rage. <dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“Now you are mine”</dialogue>, said the lad; and so he got the Princess to <action actor="Boots" subject="Princess" sign="positive">wife</action>, and
                half the kingdom.</p>
        </body>
    </story>
    <story>
    <title>TATTERHOOD</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time there was a <character who="King Queen">king and a queen</character>
            <descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="King Queen" sign="neutral">who had no
                children</descriptor>, <descriptor subject="Queen" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">and that gave the queen much grief; she scarce had one happy
                hour. She was always bewailing and bemoaning herself, and saying how dull and
                lonesome it was in the palace.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="herself">“If we had children there’d be life enough”,
                she said.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Wherever she went in all her realm she found God’s blessing in children, even in the
            vilest hut; and wherever she came she heard the Goodies scolding the bairns, and saying
            how they had done that and that wrong. All this the queen heard, and thought it would be
            so nice to do as other women did. <action actor="King Queen" subject="adopted daughter"
                sign="positive">At last the <character who="King Queen">king and queen</character>
                took into their palace a stranger <character who="adopted daughter"
                    >lassie</character> to rear up, that they might have her always with them, to
                love her if she did well, and scold her if she did wrong, like their own
                child.</action></p>
        <p>So one day the <character who="adopted daughter">little lassie</character> whom they had
            taken as their own, ran down into the palace yard, and was playing with a gold apple.
            Just then an <character who="old beggar wife">old beggar wife</character> came by, who
            had a <character who="beggar wife's daughter">little girl</character> with her, and it
            wasn’t long before the <character who="adopted daughter">little lassie</character> and
            the <character who="beggar wife's daughter">beggar’s bairn</character> were great
            friends, and began to play together, and to toss the gold apple about between them.
                <action actor="Queen" subject="adopted daughter" sign="neutral">When the <character
                    who="Queen">Queen</character> saw this, as she sat at a window in the palace,
                she tapped on the pane for her foster-daughter to come up.</action> She went at
            once, but the beggar-girl went up too; and as they went into the Queen’s bower, each
            held the other by the hand. <action actor="Queen" subject="adopted daughter"
                sign="negative">Then the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> began to scold the
                little lady, and to say:</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="adopted daughter">“You ought to be above running
                about and playing with a <descriptor subject="beggar wife's daughter"
                    sign="negative" speaker="Queen">tattered</descriptor> beggar’s brat.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>And so she wanted to drive the lassie downstairs.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="beggar wife's daughter" subject="Queen">“If the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> only knew my mother’s power, she’d not drive me out”, said
                the <character who="beggar wife's daughter">little lassie</character></dialogue>;
            and when the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> asked what she meant more plainly,
                <dialogue subject="Queen" speaker="beggar wife's daughter">she told her how her
                mother could get her children if she chose.</dialogue> The <character who="Queen"
                >Queen</character> wouldn’t believe it, but the <character
                who="beggar wife's daughter">lassie</character> held her own, and said every word of
            it was true, and bade the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> only to try and make
            her mother do it. <action actor="Queen" subject="beggar wife's daughter" sign="neutral"
                >So the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> sent the <character
                    who="beggar wife's daughter">lassie</character> down to fetch up her
                mother.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="old beggar wife">“Do you know what your daughter
                says?” asked the <character who="Queen">Queen</character></dialogue> of the old
            woman, as soon as ever she came into the room.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old beggar wife" subject="Queen">No</dialogue>; the beggar wife knew
            nothing about it.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="old beggar wife">“Well, she says you can get me
                children if you will”, answered the <character who="Queen"
                >Queen</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old beggar wife" subject="Queen">“Queens shouldn’t listen to beggar
                lassies’ silly stories”, said the old wife</dialogue>, and strode out of the
            room.</p>
        <p>Then the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> got angry, and wanted again to drive
            out the <character who="beggar wife's daughter">little lassie</character>; but she
            declared it was true every word that she had said.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="little girl" subject="Queen">“Let the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> only give my mother a drop to drink,” said the <character
                    who="beggar wife's daughter">lassie</character>; “when she gets merry she’ll
                soon find out a way to help you.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Queen" subject="old beggar wife" sign="positive">The <character
                    who="Queen">Queen</character> was ready to try this; so the <character
                    who="old beggar wife">beggar wife</character> was fetched up again once more,
                and treated both with wine and mead as much as she chose; and so it was not long
                before her tongue began to wag. Then the <character who="Queen">Queen</character>
                came out again with the same question she had asked before.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old beggar wife" subject="Queen">“One way to help you perhaps I
                know”, said the beggar wife. “Your Majesty must make them bring in two pails of
                water some evening before you go to bed. In each of them you must wash yourself, and
                afterwards throw away the water under the bed. When you look under the bed next
                morning, <descriptor subject="flowers" sign="neutral" speaker="old beggar wife">two
                    flowers will have sprung up, one fair and one ugly.</descriptor> The fair one
                you must eat, the ugly one you must let stand; but mind you don’t forget the
                last.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>That was what the <character who="old beggar wife">beggar wife</character> said.</p>
        <p><action actor="Queen" subject="flowers" sign="neutral">Yes; the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> did what the beggar wife advised her to do; she had the water
                brought up in two pails, washed herself in them, and emptied them under the bed; and
                lo! when she looked under the bed next morning, there stood two flowers; <descriptor
                    subject="ugly flower" sign="negative" speaker="Queen">one was ugly and foul, and
                    had black leaves;</descriptor>
                <descriptor subject="pretty flower" sign="positive" speaker="Queen">but the other
                    was so bright, and fair, and lovely, she had never seen its like;</descriptor>
                so she ate it up at once. <action actor="Queen" subject="ugly flower"
                    sign="negative">But the pretty flower tasted so sweet, that she couldn’t help
                    herself. She ate the other up too,</action> for, she thought,</action>
            <dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="herself">“it can’t hurt or help one much either way,
                I’ll be bound”.</dialogue></p>
        <p>Well, sure enough, after a while the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> was brought
            to bed. <descriptor subject="Queen" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">First of all, she
                had a <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative"
                    >girl</descriptor> who had a wooden spoon in her hand, and rode upon a goat;
                loathly and ugly she was, and the very moment she came into the world</descriptor>,
            she bawled out <dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Queen">“Mamma”</dialogue>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="Tatterhood"><descriptor subject="Tatterhood"
                    sign="negative" speaker="Queen">“If I’m your mamma”, said the <character
                        who="Queen">Queen</character>, “God give me grace to mend my
                    ways.”</descriptor></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Queen">“Oh, don’t be sorry”, said the girl, who
                rode on the goat, “for one will soon come after me who is better
                looking.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So, after a while, <descriptor subject="Queen" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">the
                    <character who="Queen">Queen</character> had <character>another
                girl</character></descriptor>, <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="younger twin"
                sign="neutral">who was so fair and sweet, no one had ever set eyes on such a lovely
                child</descriptor>, and with her you may fancy the <character who="Queen"
                >Queen</character> was very well pleased. The <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="Tatterhood" sign="neutral"><descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="neutral"
                    speaker="narrator">elder twin</descriptor> they called “<character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>”, because she was always so ugly and
                ragged, and because she had a hood which hung about her ears in
            tatters</descriptor>. <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative" speaker="Queen"
                >The <character who="Queen">Queen</character> could scarce bear to look at her, and
                the nurses tried to shut her up in a room by herself, <descriptor
                    subject="younger twin and Tatterhood" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">but it
                    was all no good; where the younger twin was, there she must also be, and no one
                    could ever keep them apart.</descriptor></descriptor></p>
        <p><descriptor subject="Christmas eve" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">Well, one
                Christmas eve, <descriptor subject="Tatterhood and younger twin" sign="" speaker=""
                    >when they were half grown up</descriptor>, there rose such a frightful noise
                and clatter in the gallery outside the Queen’s bower.</descriptor>
            <dialogue subject="Queen" speaker="Tatterhood">So <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> asked what it was that dashed and crashed so out in the
                passage.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="Tatterhood">“Oh!” said the Queen, “it isn’t worth
                asking about.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>But <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> wouldn’t give over till she found
            out all about it and <dialogue subject="Tatterhood" speaker="Queen">so the <character
                    who="Queen">Queen</character> told her it was a pack of Trolls and witches who
                had come there to keep Christmas.</dialogue>
            <dialogue subject="Queen" speaker="Tatterhood">So <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> said she’d just go out and drive them away;</dialogue>
            and in spite of all they could say, and however much they begged and prayed her to let
            the Trolls alone, she must and would go out to drive the witches off; but <dialogue
                speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Queen">she begged the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> to mind and keep all the doors close shut, so that not one of
                them came so much as the least bit ajar.</dialogue> Having said this, <action
                actor="Tatterhood" subject="trolls and witches" sign="positive">off she went with
                her wooden spoon, and began to hunt and sweep away the hags</action>; <descriptor
                subject="palace" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">and all this while there was
                such a pother out in the gallery, the like of it was never heard. The whole Palace
                creaked and groaned as if every joint and beam were going to be torn out of its
                place. Now, how it was, I’m sure I can’t tell; but somehow or other one door did get
                the least bit ajar,</descriptor>
            <action actor="witch" subject="younger twin" sign="negative">then <character
                    who="younger twin">her twin sister</character> just peeped out to see how things
                were going with <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>, and put her head
                a tiny bit through the opening. But, POP! up came an old witch, and whipped off her
                head, and stuck a calf’s head on her shoulders instead; and <descriptor
                    subject="younger twin" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">so the <character
                        who="younger twin">Princess</character> ran back into the room on all-fours,
                    and began to “moo” like a calf.</descriptor></action> When <character
                who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> came back and saw her sister, she scolded
            them all round, and was very angry because they hadn’t kept better watch, and asked them
            what they thought of their heedlessness now, when her sister was turned into a calf.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="everyone">“But still I’ll see if I can’t set her
                free”, she said.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">Then she asked the King for a ship in full trim, and well fitted with stores; but captain
            and sailors she wouldn’t have. No; she would sail away with her sister all alone; and as
            there was no holding her back, at last they let her have her own way.</descriptor></p>
        <p><action actor="Tatterhood" subject="ship" sign="positive">Then <character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> sailed off, and steered her ship right
                under the land where the witches dwelt, and when she came to the landing-place, she
                told her sister to stay quite still on board the ship;</action>
            <action actor="Tatterhood" subject="witches" sign="positive">but she herself rode on her
                goat up to the witches’ castle. When she got there, one of the windows in the
                gallery was open, and there she saw her sister’s head hung up on the window frame;
                so she leapt her goat through the window into the gallery, snapped up the head, and
                set off with it. After her came the witches to try to get the head again, and they
                flocked about her as thick as a swarm of bees or a nest of ants; but the goat
                snorted, and puffed, and butted with his horns, and <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> beat and banged them about with her wooden spoon; and so
                the pack of witches had to give it up.</action>
            <action actor="Tatterhood" subject="younger twin" sign="positive">So <character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> got back to her ship, took the calf’s
                head off her sister, and put her own on again, and then she became a girl as she had
                been before.</action> After that she sailed a long, long way, to a strange king’s
            realm.</p>
        <p>Now the <character who="foreign king">king</character> of that land <descriptor
                subject="foreign king" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">was a widower, and had an
                only son.</descriptor>
            <action actor="foreign king" subject="foreign king's men" sign="neutral">So when he saw
                the strange sail, he sent <character who="foreign king's men">messengers</character>
                down to the strand to find out whence it came, and who owned it; but when the
                    <character who="foreign king's men">king’s men</character> came down there,
                    <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="positive" speaker="foreign king's men"
                    >they saw never a living soul on board but <character who="Tatterhood"
                        >Tatterhood</character>, and there she was, riding round and round the deck
                    on her goat at full speed, till her elf locks streamed again in the
                    wind.</descriptor></action> The folk from the palace were all amazed at this
            sight, <dialogue subject="Tatterhood" speaker="foreign king's men">and asked, were there
                not more on board?</dialogue>
            <dialogue subject="foreign king's men" speaker="Tatterhood">Yes, there were; she had a
                sister with her, said Tatterhood.</dialogue> Her, too, they wanted to see, <dialogue
                subject="foreign king's men" speaker="Tatterhood">but <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> said “No”:</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="foreign king's men">“No one shall see her, unless
                the king comes himself”, she said;</dialogue> and so <descriptor
                subject="Tatterhood" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">she began to gallop about on
                her goat till the deck thundered again.</descriptor></p>
        <p><action actor="foreign king's men" subject="foreign king" sign="neutral">So when the
                servants got back to the palace, and told what they had seen and heard down at the
                ship,</action>
            <action actor="foreign king" subject="ship" sign="neutral">the <character
                    who="foreign king">king</character> was for setting out at once, that he might
                see the lassie that rode on the goat. When he got down, <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> led out her sister, and she was so fair and gentle, the
                    <descriptor subject="younger twin" sign="positive" speaker="foreign king"
                        ><character who="foreign king">king</character> fell over head and ears in
                    love with her as he stood. He brought them both back with him to the Palace, and
                    wanted to have the sister for his queen;</descriptor></action> but <character
                who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> said <dialogue speaker="Tatterhood"
                subject="King">“No”; the <character who="foreign king">king</character> couldn’t
                have her in any way, unless the <character who="Prince">king’s son</character> chose
                to have <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>.</dialogue> That you may
            fancy the <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative" speaker="narrator"><character
                    who="Prince">prince</character> was very loath to do,</descriptor>
            <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">such an ugly hussy as
                    <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> was;</descriptor> but at last
            the <character who="foreign king">king</character> and all the others in the palace
            talked him over, and he yielded, giving his word to take her for his queen; but it went
            sore against the grain, and he was a doleful man.</p>
        <p>Now they set about the wedding, both with brewing and baking; and when all was ready,
            they were to go to church; but the <character who="Prince">prince</character> thought it
            the weariest churching he had ever had in all his life. <descriptor
                subject="foreign king and younger twin" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">First,
                the <character who="foreign king">king</character> drove off with his bride, and she
                was so lovely and so grand, all the people stopped to look after her all along the
                road, and they stared at her till she was out of sight.</descriptor>
            <descriptor subject="Tatterhood Prince" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">After them
                came the <character who="Prince">prince</character> on horseback by the side of
                    <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>, who trotted along on her
                goat with her wooden spoon in her fist, and to look at him, it was more like going
                to a burial than a wedding, and that his own; so sorrowful he seemed, and with never
                a word to say.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Why don’t you talk?” asked <character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>, when they had ridden a bit.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why, what should I talk about?”
                answered the <character who="Prince">prince</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Well, you might at least ask me why I
                ride upon this ugly goat”, said <character who="Tatterhood"
                >Tatterhood</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why do you ride on that <descriptor
                    subject="goat" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">ugly goat</descriptor>?” asked
                the <character who="Prince">prince</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Is it an ugly goat? why, it’s the
                grandest horse bride ever rode on”, answered <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character>;</dialogue>
            <misconception actor="Prince" subject="goat" sign="positive">and in a trice the goat
                became a horse, and that the finest the <character who="Prince">prince</character>
                had ever set eyes on.</misconception>
        </p>
        <p>Then they rode on again a bit, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">but the <character who="Prince">prince</character> was just as
                woeful as before, and couldn’t get a word out.</descriptor>
            <dialogue subject="Prince" speaker="Tatterhood">So <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> asked him again why he didn’t talk,</dialogue> and when
                <dialogue subject="Tatterhood" speaker="Prince">the Prince answered he didn’t know
                what to talk about,</dialogue> she said:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“You can at least ask me why I ride with
                this ugly spoon in my fist.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why do you ride with that <descriptor
                    subject="wand" sign="negative" speaker="Prince"/>ugly spoon? “asked the
                    <character who="Prince">prince</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Is it an ugly spoon? why, it’s the
                loveliest silver wand bride ever bore”, said <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character>;</dialogue>
            <misconception actor="Prince" subject="wand" sign="positive"> and in a trice it became a
                silver wand, so dazzling bright, the sunbeams glistened from it.</misconception>
        </p>
        <p>So they rode on another bit, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">but the Prince was just as sorrowful, and said never a
                word.</descriptor> In a little while, <dialogue subject="Prince"
                speaker="Tatterhood"><character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> asked him
                again why he didn’t talk, and bade him ask why she wore that ugly grey hood on her
                head.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why do you wear that <descriptor
                    subject="hood" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">ugly grey hood on your
                    head</descriptor>?” asked the Prince.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Is it an ugly hood? why, it’s the
                brightest golden crown bride ever wore”, answered <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character>,</dialogue>
            <misconception actor="Prince" subject="hood" sign="positive"> and it became a crown on
                the spot.</misconception>
        </p>
        <p>Now, they rode on a long while again, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">and the Prince was so woeful, that he sat without sound or speech
                just as before.</descriptor>
            <dialogue subject="Prince" speaker="Tatterhood">So his bride asked him again why he
                didn’t talk, and bade him ask now, why her face was so ugly and
                ashen-grey?</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Ah!” asked the Prince, “why is
                    <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">your face so
                    ugly and ashen-grey</descriptor>?”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“I ugly”, said the bride; “you think my
                sister pretty, but I am ten times prettier”;</dialogue> and lo!<misconception
                actor="Prince" subject="Tatterhood" sign="positive"> when the Prince looked at her,
                she was so lovely, he thought there never was so lovely a woman in all the
                world.</misconception> After that, I shouldn’t wonder if the Prince found his
            tongue, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">and no longer
                rode along hanging down his head.</descriptor></p>
        <p>So they drank the bridal cup both deep and long, and, after that, both <character
                who="Prince">Prince</character> and King set out with their brides to the Princess’s
            father’s palace, and there they had another bridal feast, and drank anew, both deep and
            long. There was no end to the fun; and, if you make haste and run to the King’s palace,
            I dare say you’ll find there’s still a drop of the bridal ale left for you.</p>
    </body>
</story>
    <story>
    <title>THE MASTER THIEF</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once upon a time there was a <character who="Cottager">poor cottager</character> who had
            three sons. He had nothing to leave them when he died, and no money with which to put
            them to any trade, so that he did not know what to make of them. At last he said he
            would give them leave to take to anything each liked best, and to go whithersoever they
            pleased, and he would go with them a bit of the way; and so he did. He went with them
            till they came to a place where three roads met, and there each of them chose a road,
            and their father bade them good-bye, and went back home. I have never heard tell what
            became of the two elder; but as for <character who="The Youth">the youngest</character>,
            he went both far and long, as you shall hear.</p>
        <p>So it fell out one night as he was going through a great wood that such bad weather
            overtook him. It blew, and sleeted, and drove so that he could scarce keep his eyes
            open; and in a trice, before he knew how it was, he got bewildered, and could not find
            either road or path. But as he went on and on, at last he saw a glimmering of light far
            far off in the wood. So he thought he would try and get to the light; and after a time
            he did reach it. There it was in a large house, and the fire was blazing so brightly
            inside, that he could tell the folk had not yet gone to bed; so he went in and saw an
                <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character> bustling about and minding the
            house.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="The Youth" subject="Old Dame">“Good evening!”</dialogue> said
                <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Old Dame" subject="The Youth">“Good evening!</dialogue>” said the
                <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Old Dame" speaker="The Youth">“Hutetu! it’s such foul weather out of
                doors to-night”</dialogue>, said he. </p>
        <p><dialogue subject="The Youth" speaker="Old Dame">“So it is”</dialogue>, said she.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Old Dame" speaker="The Youth">“Can I get leave to have a bed and
                shelter here to-night?”</dialogue> asked <character who="The Youth">the
                youth</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="The Youth" speaker="Old Dame">“You’ll get no good by sleeping
                here”</dialogue>, said the <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character>; <dialogue
                subject="The Youth" speaker="Old Dame">“for if the folk come home and find you here,
                they’ll kill both me and you.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Old Dame" speaker="The Youth">“What sort of folk, then, are they who
                live here?”</dialogue> asked <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Old Dame" subject="The Youth">“Oh, robbers! And a bad lot of them
                too”</dialogue>, said the <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character>. <dialogue
                speaker="Old Dame" subject="The Youth">“They stole me away when I was little, and
                have kept me as their housekeeper ever since.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="The Youth" subject="Old Dame">“Well, for all that, I think I’ll just
                go to bed”</dialogue>, said <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>.
                <dialogue speaker="The Youth" subject="Old Dame">“Come what may, I’ll not stir out
                at night in such weather.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Old Dame" subject="The Youth">“Very well”</dialogue>, said the
                <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character>; <dialogue speaker="Old Dame"
                subject="The Youth">“but if you stay, it will be the worse for you.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>With that <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> got into a bed which stood
            there, but he dared not go to sleep, and very soon after in came <character
                who="Robbers">the robbers</character>; so the <character who="Old Dame">old
                dame</character> told them how a stranger fellow had come in whom she had not been
            able to get out of the house again.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Old Dame" speaker="Robbers">“Did you see if he had any
                money?”</dialogue> said <character who="Robbers">the robbers</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Old Dame" subject="Robbers">“Such a one as he money!”</dialogue> said
            the <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character>, <dialogue subject="Robbers"
                speaker="Old Dame">“<descriptor speaker="Old Dame" subject="The Youth"
                    sign="Negative">the tramper</descriptor>! Why, if he had clothes to his back, it
                was as much as he had.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Then <character who="Robbers">the robbers</character> began to talk among themselves what
            they should do with him; if they should kill him outright, or what else they should do.
            Meantime <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> got up and began to talk to
            them, and to ask if they didn’t want a servant, for it might be that <action
                subject="Robbers" actor="The Youth" sign="Positive">he would be glad to enter their
                service</action>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Robbers" subject="The Youth">“Oh”</dialogue>, said they, <dialogue
                speaker="Robbers" subject="The Youth">“if you have a mind to follow the trade that
                we follow, you can very well get a place here.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="The Youth" subject="Robbers">“It’s all one to me what trade I
                follow”</dialogue>, said <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>; <dialogue
                subject="Robbers" speaker="The Youth">“for when I left home, father gave me leave to
                take to any trade I chose.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Robbers" subject="The Youth">“Well, have you a mind to
                steal?”</dialogue> asked the robbers.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="The Youth" subject="Robbers">“I don’t care”</dialogue>, said
                <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>, for he thought it would not take
            long to learn that trade.</p>
        <p>Now there lived<character who="Rancher"> a man a little way off who had three
                oxen</character>. One of these he was to take to the town to sell, and <character
                who="Robbers">the robbers</character> had heard what he was going to do, so they
            said to <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>, if he were good to steal the
            ox from the man by the way without his knowing it, and without doing him any harm, they
            would give him leave to be their serving-man.</p>
        <p>Well! <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> set off, and <action
                subject="Robbers" actor="The Youth" sign="Negative">took</action> with him a pretty
            shoe, with a silver buckle on it, which lay about the house; and he put the shoe in the
            road along which <character who="Rancher">the man</character> was going with his ox; and
            when he had done that, he went into the wood and hid himself under a bush. So when the
            man came by he saw the shoe at once.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="Self">“That’s a nice shoe”</dialogue>, said he.
                <dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="Self">“If I only had the fellow to it, I’d take
                it home with me, and perhaps I’d put my <character who="Rancher's Wife">old
                    dame</character> in a good humour for once.”</dialogue> For you must know he had
            an old wife, so <descriptor subject="Rancher's Wife" speaker="Narrator" sign="Negative"
                >cross and snappish</descriptor>, it was not long between each time that she boxed
            his ears. But then he bethought him that he could do nothing with the odd shoe unless he
            had the fellow to it; so he went on his way and let the shoe lie on the road.</p>
        <p>Then <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> took up the shoe, and made all the
            haste he could to get before the man by a short cut through the wood, and laid it down
            before him in the road again. When the man came along with his ox, <action
                actor="Rancher" subject="Self" sign="Negative">he got quite angry with
                himself</action> for being so <descriptor speaker="Self" subject="Rancher"
                sign="Negative">dull</descriptor> as to leave the fellow to the shoe lying in the
            road instead of taking it with him; so he tied the ox to the fence, and said to himself,
                <dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="Self">“I may just as well run back and pick up
                the other, and then I’ll have a pair of good shoes for my <character
                    who="Rancher's Wife">old dame</character>, and so, perhaps, I’ll get a kind word
                from her for once.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So he set off, and hunted and hunted up and down for the shoe, but no shoe did he find;
            and at length he had to go back with the one he had. But, meanwhile <character
                who="The Youth">the youth</character> had <action actor="The Youth"
                subject="Rancher" sign="Negative">taken the ox</action> and gone off with it; and
            when the man came and saw his ox gone, he began to cry and bewail, for he was afraid his
                <character who="Rancher's Wife">old dame</character> would kill him outright when
            she came to know that the ox was lost. But just then it came across his mind that he
            would go home and take the second ox, and drive it to the town, and not let his
                <character who="Old Dame">old dame</character> know anything about the matter. So he
            did this, and went home and took the ox without his dame’s knowing it, and set off with
            it to the town. But <character who="Robbers">the robbers</character> knew all about it,
            and they said to <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>, if he could get this
            ox too, without the man’s knowing it, and without his doing him any harm, he should be
            as good as any one of them. If that were all, <character who="The Youth">the
                youth</character> said, he did not think it a very hard thing.</p>
        <p>This time he took with him a rope, and hung himself up under the arm-pits to a tree right
            in the man’s way. So the man came along with his ox, and when he saw such a sight
            hanging there he began to feel a little queer.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="The Youth">“Well”</dialogue>, said he, <dialogue
                speaker="Rancher" subject="The Youth">“whatever heavy thoughts you had who have
                hanged yourself up there, it can’t be helped; you may hang for what I care! I can’t
                breathe life into you again”</dialogue>; and with that he went on his way with his
            ox. Down slipped the youth from the tree, and ran by a footpath, and got before the man,
            and hung himself up right in his way again.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="The Youth">“Bless me!”</dialogue> said the man,
                <dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="The Youth">“were you really so heavy at heart
                that you hanged yourself up there—or is it only a piece of witchcraft that I see
                before me? Aye, aye! you may hang for all I care, whether you are a ghost or
                whatever you are.”</dialogue> So he passed on with his ox.</p>
        <p>Now <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> did just as he had done twice
            before; he jumped down from the tree, ran through the wood by a footpath, and hung
            himself up right in the man’s way again. But when the man saw this sight for the third
            time, he said to himself:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="The Youth">“Well! this is an ugly business! Is it
                likely now that they should have been so heavy at heart as to hang themselves, all
                these three? No! I cannot think it is anything else than a piece of witchcraft that
                I see. But now I’ll soon know for certain; if the other two are still hanging there,
                it must be really so; but if they are not, then it can be nothing but witchcraft
                that I see.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So he tied up his ox, and ran back to see if the others were still really hanging there.
            But while he went and peered up into all the trees, <character who="The Youth">the
                youth</character> jumped down and <action subject="Rancher" actor="The Youth"
                sign="Negative">took his ox</action> and ran off with it. When the man came back and
            found his ox gone, he was in a sad plight, and, as any one might know without being
            told, he began to cry and bemoan; but at last he came to take it easier, and so he
            thought:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rancher" subject="Self">“There’s no other help for it than to go home
                and take the third ox without my dame’s knowing it, and to try and drive a good
                bargain with it, so that I may get a good sum of money for it.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So he went home and set off with the ox, and his <character who="Rancher's Wife">old
                dame</character> knew never a word about the matter. But <character who="Robbers"
                >the robbers</character>, they knew all about it, and they said to <character
                who="The Youth">the youth</character>, that if he could steal this ox as he had
            stolen the other two, then he should be master over the whole band. Well, <character
                who="The Youth">the youth</character> set off, and ran into the wood; and as the man
            came by with his ox he set up a dreadful bellowing, just like a great ox in the wood.
            When the man heard that, you can’t think how glad he was, for it seemed to him that he
            knew the voice of his big bullock, and he thought that now he should find both of them
            again; so he tied up the third ox, and ran off from the road to look for them in the
            wood; but meantime <character who="The Youth">the youth</character><action
                subject="Rancher" actor="The Youth" sign="Negative"> went off with the third
                ox</action>. Now, when the man came back and found he had lost this ox too, he was
            so wild that there was no end to his grief. He cried and roared and beat his breast,
            and, to tell the truth, it was many days before he dared go home; for he was afraid lest
            his <character who="Rancher's Wife">old dame</character> should kill him outright on the spot.</p>
            <p>As for <character who="Robbers">the robbers</character>, they were not very well pleased
            either, when they had to own that <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> was
            master over the whole band. So one day they thought they would try their hands at
            something which he was not man enough to do; and they set off all together, every man
            Jack of them, and left him alone at home. Now, the first thing that he did when they
            were all well clear of the house, was to drive the oxen out to the road, so that they
            might run back to the man from whom he had stolen them; and right glad he was to see
            them, as you may fancy. Next he took all the horses which <character who="Robbers">the
                robbers</character> had, and loaded them with the best things he could lay his hands
            on-gold and silver, and clothes and other fine things; and then he bade the <character
                who="Old Dame">old dame</character> to greet <character who="Robbers">the
                robbers</character> when they came back, and to thank them for him, and to say that
            now he was setting off on his travels, and they would have hard work to find him again;
            and with that, off he started.</p> 
            <p>After a good bit he came to the road along which he was
            going when he fell among the robbers, and when he got near home, and could see his
            father’s cottage, he put on a uniform which he had found among the clothes he had taken
            from <character who="Robbers">the robbers</character>, and which was made just like a
            general’s. So he drove up to the door as if he were any other great man. After that he
            went in and asked if he could have a lodging? No; that he couldn’t at any price.</p>
            <p>“How ever should I be able”, said the man, “to make room in my house for such a fine
            gentleman—I who scarce have a rag to lie upon, and miserable rags too?”</p> 
            <p>“You always were a stingy old hunks”, said <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>, “and so you
            are still, when you won’t take your own son in.”</p>
            <p>“What, you my son!” said the man.</p> 
            <p>“Don’t you know me again?” said <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>. Well,
            after a little while he did know him again.</p>
            <p>“But what have you been turning your hand to, that you have made yourself so great a man in such haste?” asked the man.</p>
            <p>“Oh! I’ll soon tell you”, said <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>. “You said I might
            take to any trade I chose, and so I bound myself apprentice to a pack of thieves and
            robbers, and now I’ve served my time out, and am become a <character who="Master Thief"
                >Master Thief</character>.”</p>
            <p>Now there lived a <character who="Squire">Squire</character> close by to his father’s cottage, and he had such a great house,
            and such heaps of money, he could not tell how much he had. He had a daughter too, and a
            smart and pretty girl she was. So the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character> set his heart upon having her to wife, and he told his father to
            go to the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> and ask for his daughter for him.</p>
            <p>“If he asks by what trade I get my living, you can say I’m a <character
                who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character>.”</p>
            <p>“I think you’ve lost your wits”, said the man, “for you can’t be in your right mind when you think of such stuff.”</p>
            <p>No! he had not lost his wits, his father must and should go to the <character who="Squire"
                >Squire</character>, and ask for his daughter.</p>
            <p>“Nay, but I tell you, I daren’t go to the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> and be your spokesman; he who is so rich,
            and has so much money”, said the man.</p>
            <p>Yes, there was no help for it, said the <character
                who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character>; he should go whether he would or no;
            and if he did not go by fair means, he would soon make him go by foul. But the man was
            still loath to go; so he stepped after him, and rubbed him down with a good birch
            cudgel, and kept on till the man came crying and sobbing inside the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character>’s door.</p>
            <p>“How now, my man! what ails you?” said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>. So he told him the whole story; how he
            had three sons who set off one day, and how he had given them leave to go whithersoever
            they would, and to follow whatever calling they chose. “And here now is the youngest
            come home, and has thrashed me till he has made me come to you and ask for your daughter
            for him to wife; and he bids me say, besides, that he’s a Master Thief.” And so he fell
            to crying and sobbing again.</p>
            <p>“Never mind, my man”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>, laughing; “just go back and tell him from me, he must prove his
            skill first. If he can steal the roast from the spit in the kitchen on Sunday, while all
            the household are looking after it, he shall have my daughter. Just go and tell him
            that.”</p>
            <p>So he went back and told <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>, who
            thought it would be an easy job. So he set about and caught three hares alive, and put
            them into a bag, and dressed himself in some old rags, until he looked so poor and
            filthy that it made one’s heart bleed to see; and then he stole into the passage at the
            back-door of the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s house on the Sunday
            forenoon, with his bag, just like any other beggar-boy. But the <character who="Squire"
                >Squire</character> himself and all his household were in the kitchen watching the
            roast. Just as they were doing this, <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>
            let one hare go, and it set off and ran round and round the yard in front of the house.</p>
            <p>“Oh, just look at that hare!” said the folk in the kitchen, and were all for running out
            to catch it.</p> 
            <p>Yes, the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> saw it running too.
            “Oh, let it run”, said he; “there’s no use in thinking to catch a hare on the spring.”</p>
            <p>A little while after, <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> let the second hare
            go, and they saw it in the kitchen, and thought it was the same they had seen before,
            and still wanted to run out and catch it; but the <character who="Squire"
                >Squire</character> said again it was no use. It was not long before <character
                who="The Youth">the youth</character> let the third hare go, and it set off and ran
            round and round the yard as the others before it. Now, they saw it from the kitchen, and
            still thought it was the same hare that kept on running about, and were all eager to be
            out after it.</p>
            <p>“Well, it is a fine hare”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>; “come let’s see if we can’t lay our hands on it.”</p>
            <p>So out he ran, and the rest with him—away they all went, the hare before, and they after; so that
            it was rare fun to see. But meantime <character who="The Youth">the youth</character>
            took the roast and ran off with it; and where the <character who="Squire"
                >Squire</character> got a roast for his dinner that day I don’t know; but one thing
            I know, and that is, that he had no roast hare, though he ran after it till he was both
            warm and weary.</p>
            <p>Now it chanced that the Priest came to dinner that day, and when the
                <character who="Squire">Squire</character> told him what a trick the <character
                who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> had played him, he made such game of him
            that there was no end of it.</p>
            <p>“For my part”, said the Priest, “I can’t think how it could
            ever happen to me to be made such a fool of by a fellow like that.”</p>
            <p>“Very well—only keep a sharp look-out”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>; “maybe he’ll
            come to see you before you know a word of it.” But the Priest stuck to his text—that he
            did, and made game of the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> because he had been
            so taken in.</p>
            <p>Later in the afternoon came the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character>, and wanted to have the <character who="Squire"
            >Squire</character>’s daughter, as he had given his word. But the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character> began to talk him over, and said, “Oh, you must
            first prove your skill a little more; for what you did to-day was no great thing, after
            all. Couldn’t you now play off a good trick on the Priest, who is sitting in there, and
            making game of me for letting such a fellow as you twist me round his thumb.”</p>
            <p>“Well, as for that, it wouldn’t be hard”, said the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character>. So he dressed himself up like a bird, threw a great white sheet
            over his body, took the wings of a goose and tied them to his back, and so climbed up
            into a great maple which stood in the Priest’s garden. And when the Priest came home in
            the evening, <character who="The Youth">the youth</character> began to bawl out:</p>
            <p>“Father Laurence! Father Laurence!”—for that was the Priest’s name.</p>
            <p>“Who is that calling me?” said the Priest.</p>
            <p>“I am an angel”, said the Master Thief, “sent from God to let you know
            that you shall be taken up alive into heaven for your piety’s sake. Next Monday night
            you must hold yourself ready for the journey, for I shall come then to fetch you in a
            sack; and all your gold and your silver, and all that you have of this world’s goods,
            you must lay together in a heap in your dining-room.”</p>
            <p>Well, Father Laurence fell on his knees before the angel, and thanked him; and the very next day he preached a farewell
            sermon, and gave it out how there had come down an angel unto the big maple in his
            garden, who had told him that he was to be taken up alive into heaven for his piety’s
            sake; and he preached and made such a touching discourse, that all who were at church
            wept, both young and old.</p>
            <p>So the next Monday night came the <character
                who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> like an angel again, and the Priest fell
            on his knees and thanked him before he was put into the sack; but when he had got him
            well in, the Master Thief drew and dragged him over stocks and stones.</p>
            <p>“OW! OW!” groaned the Priest inside the sack, “wherever are we going?”</p>
            <p>“This is the narrow way which leadeth unto the kingdom of heaven”, said the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character>, who went on dragging him along till he had nearly broken every
            bone in his body. At last he tumbled him into a goose-house that belonged to the
                <character who="Squire">Squire</character>, and the geese began pecking and pinching
            him with their bills, so that he was more dead than alive.</p>
            <p>“Now you are in the flames of purgatory, to be cleansed and purified for life everlasting”, said the Master Thief; and
            with that he went his way, and took all the gold which the Priest had laid together in
            his dining-room. The next morning, when the goose-girl came to let the geese out, she
            heard how the Priest lay in the sack, and bemoaned himself in the goose-house.</p>
            <p>“In heaven’s name, who’s there, and what ails you?” she cried.</p>
            <p>“Oh!” said the Priest, “if you are an angel from heaven, do let me out, and let me return again to earth, for it is
            worse here than in hell. The little fiends keep on pinching me with tongs.”</p>
            <p>“Heaven help us, I am no angel at all”, said the girl, as she helped the Priest out of the sack; “I
            only look after the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s geese, and like enough
            they are the little fiends which have pinched your reverence.”</p>
            <p>“Oh!” groaned the Priest, “this is all that <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character>’s doing. Ah! my
            gold and my silver, and my fine clothes.” And he beat his breast, and hobbled home at
            such a rate that the girl thought he had lost his wits all at once.</p>
            <p>Now when the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> came to hear how it had gone with the
            Priest, and how he had been along the narrow way, and into purgatory, he laughed till he
            well-nigh split his sides. But when the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character> came and asked for his daughter as he had promised, the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character> put him off again, and said:</p>
            <p>“You must do one masterpiece better still, that I may see plainly what you are fit for. Now, I have
            twelve horses in my stable, and on them I will put twelve grooms, one on each. If you
            are so good a thief as to steal the horses from under them, I’ll see what I can do for
            you.”</p>
            <p>“Very well, I daresay I can do it”, said the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character>; “but shall I really have your daughter if I can?”</p>
            <p>“Yes, if you can, I’ll do my best for you”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>. So
            the <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> set off to a shop, and bought
            brandy enough to fill two pocket-flasks, and into one of them he put a sleepy drink, but
            into the other only brandy. After that he hired eleven men to lie in wait at night,
            behind the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s stable-yard; and last of all,
            for fair words and a good bit of money, he borrowed a ragged gown and cloak from an old
            woman; and so, with a staff in his hand, and a bundle at his back, he limped off, as
            evening drew on, towards the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s stable. Just
            as he got there they were watering the horses for the night, and had their hands full of
            work. “What the devil do you want?” said one of the grooms to the old woman.</p>
            <p>“Oh, oh! hutetu! it is so bitter cold”, said she, and shivered and shook, and made wry faces.
            “Hutetu! it is so cold, a poor wretch may easily freeze to death”; and with that she
            fell to shivering and shaking again.</p>
            <p>“Oh! for the love of heaven, can I get leave to
            stay here a while, and sit inside the stable door?”</p>
            <p>“To the devil with your leave”, said one. “Pack yourself off this minute, for if the <character who="Squire"
                >Squire</character> sets his eye on you, he’ll lead us a pretty dance.”</p>
            <p>“Oh! the poor old bag-of-bones”, said another, whose heart took pity on her, “the old hag may sit
            inside and welcome; such a one as she can do no harm.”</p>
            <p>And the rest said, some she should stay, and some she shouldn’t; but while they were quarrelling and minding the
            horses, she crept further and further into the stable, till at last she sat herself down
            behind the door; and when she had got so far, no one gave any more heed to her.</p>
            <p>As the night wore on, the men found it rather cold work to sit so still and quiet on horseback.</p>
            <p>“Hutetu! it is so devilish cold”, said one, and beat his arms crosswise.</p>
            <p>“That it is”, said another; “I freeze so, that my teeth chatter.”</p>
            <p>“If one only had a quid to chew”, said a third.</p>
            <p>Well! there was one who had an ounce or two; so they shared it between
            them, though it wasn’t much, after all, that each got; and so they chewed and spat, and
            spat and chewed. This helped them somewhat; but in a little while they were just as bad
            as ever.</p>
            <p>“Hutetu!” said one, and shivered and shook.</p>
            <p>“Hutetu!” said the old woman, and shivered so, that every tooth in her head chattered. Then she pulled out the flask with
            brandy in it, and her hand shook so that the spirit splashed about in the flask, and
            then she took such a gulp, that it went “bop” in her throat.</p>
            <p>“What’s that you’ve got in your flask, old girl?” said one of the grooms.</p>
            <p>“Oh! it’s only a drop of brandy, old man”, said she.</p>
            <p>“Brandy! Well, I never! Do let me have a drop”, screamed the whole twelve, one after another.</p> 
            <p>“Oh! but it is such a little drop”, mumbled the old woman,
            “it will not even wet your mouths round.” But they must and would have it; there was no
            help for it; and so she pulled out the flask with the sleepy drink in it, and put it to
            the first man’s lips; then she shook no more, but guided the flask so that each of them
            got what he wanted, and the twelfth had not done drinking before the first sat and
            snored. Then the <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> threw off his
            beggar’s rags, and took one groom after the other so softly off their horses, and set
            them astride on the beams between the stalls; and so he called his eleven men, and rode
            off with the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s twelve horses. But when the
                <character who="Squire">Squire</character> got up in the morning, and went to look
            after his grooms, they had just begun to come to; and some of them fell to spurring the
            beams with their spurs, till the splinters flew again, and some fell off, and some still
            hung on and sat there looking like fools.</p>
            <p>“Ho! ho!” said the <character who="Squire"
                >Squire</character>; “I see very well who has been here; but as for you, a pretty
            set of blockheads you must be to sit here and let the <character who="Master Thief"
                >Master Thief</character> steal the horses from between your legs.”</p>
            <p>So they all got a good leathering because they had not kept a sharper look-out.</p>
            <p>Further on in the day came the <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> again, and told how he
            had managed the matter, and asked for the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s
            daughter, as he had promised; but the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> gave
            him one hundred dollars down, and said he must do something better still.</p>
            <p>“Do you think now”, said he, “you can steal the horse from under me while I am out riding on his
            back?” “O, yes! I daresay I could”, said the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character>, “if I were really sure of getting your daughter.”</p>
            <p>Well, well, the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> would see what he could do; and he told
            the <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> a day when he would be taking
            a ride on a great common where they drilled the troops. So the <character
                who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> soon got hold of an old worn-out jade of
            a mare, and set to work, and made traces and collar of withies and broom-twigs, and
            bought an old beggarly cart and a great cask. After that he told an old beggar woman, he
            would give her ten dollars if she would get inside the cask, and keep her mouth agape
            over the taphole, into which he was going to stick his finger. No harm should happen to
            her; she should only be driven about a little; and if he took his finger out more than
            once, she was to have ten dollars more. Then he threw a few rags and tatters over
            himself, and stuffed himself out, and put on a wig and a great beard of goat’s hair, so
            that no one could know him again, and set off for the common, where the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character> had already been riding about a good bit. When he
            reached the place, he went along so softly and slowly that he scarce made an inch of
            way. “Gee up! Gee up!” and so he went on a little; then he stood stock still, and so on
            a little again; and altogether the pace was so poor it never once came into the
                <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s head that this could be the <character
                who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character>.</p>
            <p>At last the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> rode right up to him, and asked if he had seen any one lurking
            about in the wood thereabouts. “No”, said the man, “I haven’t seen a soul.”</p>
            <p>“Harkye, now”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>, “if you have a mind to ride
            into the wood, and hunt about and see if you can fall upon any one lurking about there,
            you shall have the loan of my horse, and a shilling into the bargain, to drink my
            health, for your pains.”</p>
            <p>“I don’t see how I can go”, said the man, “for I am going to a
            wedding with this cask of mead, which I have been to town to fetch, and here the tap has
            fallen out by the way, and so I must go along, holding my finger in the taphole.”</p>
            <p>“Ride off”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>; “I’ll look after your horse
            and cask.”</p>
            <p>Well, on these terms the man was willing to go; but he begged the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character> to be quick in putting his finger into the taphole
            when he took his own out, and to mind and keep it there till he came back. At last the
                <character who="Squire">Squire</character> grew weary of standing there with his
            finger in the taphole, so he took it out.</p>
            <p>“Now I shall have ten dollars more!” screamed
            the old woman inside the cask; and then the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>
            saw at once how the land lay, and took himself off home; but he had not gone far before
            they met him with a fresh horse, for the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character> had already been to his house, and told them to send one. The day
            after, he came to the <character who="Squire">Squire</character> and would have his
            daughter, as he had given his word; but the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>
            put him off again with fine words, and gave him two hundred dollars, and said he must do
            one more masterpiece. If he could do that, he should have her. Well, well, the
                <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> thought he could do it, if he
            only knew what it was to be.</p>
            <p>“Do you think, now”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>, “you can steal the sheet off our bed, and the shift off my
            wife’s back. Do you think you could do that?”</p>
            <p>“It shall be done”, said the <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character>. “I only wish I was as sure of getting
            your daughter.”</p>
            <p>So when night began to fall, the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character> went out and cut down a thief who hung on the gallows, and threw
            him across his shoulders, and carried him off. Then he got a long ladder and set it up
            against the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>’s bedroom window, and so climbed
            up, and kept bobbing the dead man up and down, just for all the world like one that was
            peeping in at the window.</p>
            <p>“That’s the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character>, old lass!” said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>,
            and gave his wife a nudge on the side. “Now see if I don’t shoot him, that’s all.”</p>
            <p>So saying he took up a rifle which he had laid at his bedside.</p>
            <p>“No! no! pray don’t shoot him after telling him he might come and try”, said his wife.</p>
            <p>“Don’t talk to me, for shoot him I will”, said he; and so he lay there and aimed and aimed; but as soon as the
            head came up before the window, and he saw a little of it, so soon was it down again. At
            last he thought he had a good aim; “bang” went the gun, down fell the dead body to the
            ground with a heavy thump, and down went the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character> too as fast as he could.</p>
            <p>“Well”, said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>, “it is quite true that I am the chief magistrate in these
            parts; but people are fond of talking, and it would be a bore if they came to see this
            dead man’s body. I think the best thing to be done is that I should go down and bury
            him.”</p>
            <p>“You must do as you think best, dear”, said his wife. So the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character> got out of bed and went downstairs, and he had
            scarce put his foot out of the door before the <character who="Master Thief">Master
                Thief</character> stole in, and went straight upstairs to his wife.</p>
            <p>“Why, dear, back already!” said she, for she thought it was her husband.</p>
            <p>“O yes, I only just put him into a hole, and threw a little earth over him. It is enough that he is out of sight, for it
            is such a bad night out of doors; by-and-by I’ll do it better. But just let me have the
            sheet to wipe myself with—he was so bloody—and I have made myself in such a mess with
            him.”</p>
            <p>So he got the sheet.</p>
            <p>After a while he said:</p>
            <p>“Do you know I am afraid you must let
            me have your nightshift too, for the sheet won’t do by itself; that I can see.”</p>
            <p>So she gave him the shift also. But just then it came across his mind that he had forgotten to
            lock the house-door, so he must step down and look to that before he came back to bed,
            and away he went with both shift and sheet.</p>
            <p>A little while after came the true <character who="Squire">Squire</character>.</p>
            <p>“Why! what a time you’ve taken to lock
            the door, dear!” said his wife; “and what have you done with the sheet and shift?”</p>
            <p>“What do you say?” said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>.</p>
            <p>“Why, I am asking what you have done with the sheet and shift that you had to wipe off the blood”, said she.</p>
            <p>“What, in the Deil’s name!” said the <character who="Squire">Squire</character>, “has he
            taken me in this time too?”</p>
            <p>Next day came the Master Thief and asked for the <character
                who="Squire">Squire</character>’s daughter, as he had given his word; and then the
                <character who="Squire">Squire</character> dared not do anything else than give her
            to him, and a good lump of money into the bargain; for, to tell the truth, he was afraid
            lest the <character who="Master Thief">Master Thief</character> should steal the eyes
            out of his head, and that the people would begin to say spiteful things of him if he
            broke his word. So the Master Thief lived well and happily from that time forward. I
            don’t know whether he stole any more; but if he did, I am quite sure it was only for the
            sake of a bit of fun.</p>
    </body>
</story>
    <story>
        <title>THE COCK AND HEN THAT WENT TO THE DOVREFELL</title>
        <body>
            <p>Once on a time there was a <character>Hen</character> that had <action actor="Hen"
                subject="environment" sign="positive">flown</action> up, and <action actor="Hen"
                    subject="oak-tree" sign="positive">perched</action> on an oak-tree for the night.
                When the night came, she <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive"
                    >dreamed</action> that unless she got to the Dovrefell, the world would come to an
                end. So that very minute she <action actor="Hen" subject="environment" sign="positive"
                    >jumped</action> down, and <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive">set
                        out on her way</action>. When she had walked a bit she met a
                <character>Cock</character>.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="Cock">"Good day,
                <character>Cocky-Locky</character>"</dialogue>, said the Hen. <dialogue
                    speaker="Cock" subject="Hen">"Good day,
                    <character>Henny-Penny</character>"</dialogue>, said the Cock, <dialogue speaker="Cock"
                        subject="Hen">"whither away so early."</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="Cock">"Oh, I’m going to the Dovrefell, that the world
                    mayn’t come to an end"</dialogue>, said the Hen. <dialogue speaker="Cock"
                        subject="Hen">"Who told you that, <character>Henny-Penny</character>"</dialogue>, said
                the Cock. <dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="Cock">"I <action actor="Hen" subject="self"
                    sign="positive">sat</action> in the oak and <action actor="Hen" subject="self"
                        sign="positive">dreamt</action> it last night"</dialogue>, said the Hen.
                <dialogue speaker="Cock" subject="Hen">"I’ll go with you"</dialogue>, said the Cock.
                Well! they walked on a good bit, and then they met a <character>Duck</character>.
                <dialogue speaker="Cock" subject="Duck">"Good day,
                    <character>Ducky-Lucky</character>"</dialogue>, said the Cock. <dialogue
                        speaker="Duck" subject="Cock">"Good day,
                        <character>Cocky-Locky</character>"</dialogue>, said the Duck, <dialogue
                            speaker="Duck" subject="Cock">"whither away so early?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Cock" subject="Duck">"Oh, I’m going to the Dovrefell, that the world
                    mayn’t come to an end"</dialogue>, said the Cock. <dialogue speaker="Duck"
                        subject="Cock">"Who told you that, <character>Cocky-Locky</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Cock" subject="Duck">"Henny-Penny"</dialogue>, said the Cock. <dialogue
                    speaker="Duck" subject="Hen">"Who told you that,
                    <character>Henny-Penny</character>?"</dialogue> said the Duck. <dialogue
                        speaker="Hen" subject="Duck">"I <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive"
                            >sat</action> in the oak and <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive"
                                >dreamt</action> it last night"</dialogue>, said the Hen. <dialogue
                                    speaker="Duck" subject="Hen">"I’ll go with you"</dialogue>, said the Duck. So they
                went off together, and after a bit they met a <character>Goose</character>. <dialogue
                    speaker="Duck" subject="Goose">"Good day,
                    <character>Goosey-Poosey</character>"</dialogue>”, said the Duck. <dialogue
                        speaker="Goose" subject="Duck">"Good day,
                        <character>Ducky-Lucky</character>"</dialogue>, said the Goose, <dialogue
                            speaker="Goose" subject="Duck">"whither away so early?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Duck" subject="Goose">"I’m going to the Dovrefell, that the world
                    mayn’t come to an end"</dialogue>, said the Duck. <dialogue speaker="Goose"
                        subject="Duck">"Who told you that, <character>Ducky-Lucky</character>?"</dialogue>
                asked the Goose. <dialogue speaker="Duck" subject="Goose"
                    >"<character>Cocky-Locky.</character>"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Goose" subject="Cock">"Who told you that,
                    <character>Cocky-Locky</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Cock" subject="Goose">"<character>Henny-Penny</character>."</dialogue>”
                <dialogue speaker="Goose" subject="Hen">"How you do know that,
                    <character>Henny-Penny</character>?"</dialogue> said the Goose. <dialogue
                        speaker="Hen" subject="Goose">"I <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign = "positive">sat</action> in
                        the oak and <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive">dreamt</action> it
                        last night, <character>Goosey-Poosey</character>"</dialogue>, said the Hen. <dialogue
                            speaker="Goose" subject="Hen">"I’ll go with you"</dialogue>, said the Goose. Now when
                they had all walked along for a bit, a <character>Fox</character> met them. <dialogue
                    speaker="Goose" subject="Fox">"Good day,
                    <character>Foxsy-Cocksy</character>"</dialogue>, said the Goose. <dialogue
                        speaker="Fox" subject="Goose">"Good day,
                        <character>Goosey-Poosey</character>."</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Goose" subject="Fox">"Whither away,
                    <character>Foxy-Cocksy</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Goose">"Whither away yourself,
                    <character>Goosey-Poosey</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Goose" subject="Fox">"I’m going to the Dovrefell that the world mayn’t
                    come to an end"</dialogue>, said the Goose. <dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Goose"
                        >"Who told you that, <character>Goosey-Poosey</character>?"</dialogue> asked the Fox.
                <dialogue speaker="Goose" subject="Fox"
                    >"<character>Ducky-Lucky</character>."</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Duck">"Who told you that,
                    <character>Ducky-Lucky</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Duck" subject="Fox">"<character>Cocky-Locky</character>."</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Cock">"Who told you that,
                    <character>Cocky-Locky</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Cock" subject="Fox">"<character>Henny-Penny</character>."</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Hen">"How do you know that,
                    <character>Henny-Penny</character>?"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="Fox">"I <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign = "positive">sat</action>
                    in the oak and <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign = "positive">dreamt</action> last night, that
                    if we don’t get to the Dovrefell, the world will come to an end"</dialogue>, said the
                Hen. </p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Hen">"Stuff and nonsense"</dialogue>, said the Fox;
                <dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Hen">"the world won’t come to an end if you don’t
                    get thither. No! come home with me to my earth. That’s far better, for it’s
                    <descriptor speaker="Fox" subject="Fox's earth" sign="positive"
                        >warm</descriptor> and <descriptor speaker="Fox" subject="Fox's earth"
                            sign="positive">jolly</descriptor> there."</dialogue></p>
            <p>Well, they went home with the <character>Fox</character> to his earth, and when they got
                in, the <character>Fox</character>
                <action actor="Fox" subject="fuel" sign="negative">laid</action> on lots of fuel, so
                that they all got very sleepy.</p>
            <p>The <character>Duck</character> and the <character>Goose</character>, they <action
                actor="Duck" subject="self" sign="positive">settled</action> themselves down in a
                corner, but the <character>Cock</character> and <character>Hen</character>
                <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive">flew</action> up on a post. So when
                the <character>Goose</character> and <character>Duck</character> were well asleep, the
                <character>Fox</character>, <action actor="Fox" subject="Goose" sign="negative"
                    >took</action> the <character>Goose</character> and laid him on the embers, and
                <action actor="Fox" subject="Goose" sign="negative">roasted</action> him. The
                <character>Hen</character>
                <action actor="Hen" subject="roast" sign="positive">smelt</action> the strong roast
                meat, and <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive">sprang</action> up to a
                higher peg, and said, half asleep: <dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="self">"Faugh, what a
                    nasty smell! What a nasty smell!"</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Fox" subject="Hen">"Oh, stuff"</dialogue>, said the Fox; <dialogue
                speaker="Fox" subject="Hen">"it’s only the smoke driven down the chimney; go to sleep
                again, and hold your tongue."</dialogue> So the <character>Hen</character> went off
                to sleep again.</p>
            <p>Now the <character>Fox</character> had hardly got the <character>Goose</character> well
                down his throat, before he did the very same with the <character>Duck</character>. He
                took and laid him on the embers, and <action actor="Fox" subject="Duck" sign="negative"
                    >roasted</action> him for a dainty bit. Then the <character>hen</character> woke up
                again, and <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive">sprung</action> up to a
                higher peg still. <dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="self">"Faugh, what a nasty smell! What
                    a nasty smell!"</dialogue></p>
            <p>She said again, and then she got her eyes open, and came to see how the
                <character>Fox</character> had <action actor="Fox" subject="birds" sign="negative"
                    >eaten</action> both the twain, <character>goose</character> and
                <character>duck</character>; so she <action actor="Hen" subject="self"
                    sign="positive">flew</action> up to the highest peg of all, and perched there, and
                <action actor="Hen" subject="chimney" sign="positive">peeped</action> up through the
                chimney.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Hen" subject="Fox">"Nay, nay; just see what a lovely lot of geese
                flying yonder"</dialogue>, she said to the Fox.</p>
            <p>Out ran <character>Reynard</character> to <action actor="Fox" subject="geese"
                sign="negative">fetch</action> a fat roast. But while he was gone, the
                <character>Hen</character>
                <action actor="Hen" subject="Cock" sign="positive">woke up</action> the
                <character>Cock</character>, and <action actor="Hen" subject="Fox" sign="positive"
                    >told</action> him how it had gone with <character>Goosey-Poosey</character> and
                <character>Ducky-Lucky</character>; and so <character>Cocky-Lucky</character> and
                <character>Henny-Penny</character>
                <action actor="Hen" subject="self" sign="positive">flew</action> out through the
                chimney, and if they hadn’t got to the Dovrefell, it surely would have been all over
                with the world.</p>
        </body>
    </story>
    <story>
        <!--  Note: author refers to same character under differnet names: [old widow, mother]  [lad, son] attribute?
    put n/a in subject attribute if it something like snore-->
        <title>THE LAD WHO WENT TO THE NORTH WIND</title>
        <body>
            <p>Once on a time there was an <character>old widow</character> who had one
                <character>son</character>; and as she was <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                    subject="mother" sign="negative">poorly</descriptor> and <descriptor
                        speaker="narrator" subject="mother" sign="negative">weak</descriptor>, her son had
                to go up into the safe to fetch meal for cooking; but when he got outside the safe, and
                was just going down the steps, there came the <character>North Wind</character>, <action
                    actor="North Wind" subject="meal" sign="negative">puffing</action> and <action
                        actor="North Wind" subject="meal" sign="negative">blowing</action>, caught up the
                meal, and so away with it through the air. Then the lad went back into the safe for
                more; but when he came out again on the steps, if the <character>North Wind</character>
                didn’t come again and carry off the meal with a <action actor="North Wind"
                    subject="meal" sign="negative">puff</action>; and, more than that, he did so the
                third time. At this the lad got very <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="lad"
                    sign="negative">angry</descriptor>; and as he thought it hard that the
                <character>North Wind</character> should behave so, he thought he’d just look him
                up, and ask him to give up his meal.</p>
            <p>So off he went, but the way was long, and he <action actor="son" subject="environment"
                sign="positive">walked</action> and walked; but at last he came to the
                <character>North Wind</character>’s house.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">"Good day!"</dialogue> said the lad, <dialogue
                speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">and thank you for coming to see us
                yesterday.</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="son">"GOOD DAY!"</dialogue> answered the
                <character>North Wind</character>, for his voice was <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                    subject="North Wind" sign = "negative">loud</descriptor> and <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                        subject="North Wind" sign = "negative">gruff</descriptor>, <dialogue speaker="North Wind"
                            subject="lad">"AND THANKS FOR COMING TO SEE ME. WHAT DO YOU WANT?"</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">"Oh!"</dialogue> answered the lad, <dialogue
                speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">"I only wished to ask you to be so good as to let
                me have back that meal you took from me on the safe steps, for we haven’t much to
                live on; and if you’re to go on snapping up the morsel we have, there’ll be nothing
                for it but to starve."</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"I haven’t got your meal"</dialogue>, said the
                <character>North Wind</character>; <dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"but
                    if you are in such need, I’ll give you a cloth which will get you everything you
                    want, if you only say, “Cloth, spread yourself, and serve up all kind of good
                    dishes!” "</dialogue></p>
            <p>With this the <character>lad</character> was well <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="lad" sign = "positive">content</descriptor>. But, as the way was so long he couldn’t get home
                in one day, so he turned into an inn on the way; and when they were going to sit down to
                supper he laid the cloth on a table which stood in the corner, and said, <dialogue
                    speaker="lad" subject="cloth">"Cloth, spread yourself, and serve up all kinds of good
                    dishes."</dialogue></p>
            <p>He had scarce said so before the cloth did as it was bid; and all who stood by thought it
                a fine thing, but most of all the <character>landlady</character>. So, when all were
                fast asleep at dead of night, she took the lad’s cloth, and put another in its stead,
                just like the one he had got from the <character>North Wind</character>, but which
                couldn’t so much as serve up a bit of dry bread.</p>
            <p>So, when the <character>lad</character> woke, he <action actor="lad" subject="cloth" sign = "positive"
                >took</action> his cloth and went off with it, and that day he got home to his
                mother.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="lad" subject="mother">"Now"</dialogue>, said he, <dialogue
                speaker="lad" subject="mother">"I’ve been to the <character>North Wind</character>’s
                house, and a <descriptor speaker="lad" subject="North Wind" sign = "positive">good</descriptor> fellow
                he is, for he gave me this cloth, and when I only say to it, ‘Cloth, spread
                yourself, and serve up all kind of good dishes’, I get any sort of food I
                please."</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="old widow" subject="lad">"All very true, I daresay,"</dialogue> said
                his mother; <dialogue speaker="old widow" subject="lad">"but seeing is believing, and I
                    shan’t believe it till I see it."</dialogue></p>
            <p>So the lad made haste, drew out a table, laid the cloth on it, and said: <dialogue
                speaker="lad" subject="cloth">"Cloth, spread yourself, and serve up all kind of good
                dishes."</dialogue></p>
            <p>But never a bit of dry bread did the cloth serve up.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="lad" subject="old widow">"Well"</dialogue>, said the
                <character>lad</character>, <dialogue speaker="lad" subject="old widow">"there’s no
                    help for it but to go to the <character>North Wind</character> again"</dialogue>; and
                away he went. So he came to where the <character>North Wind</character> lived late in
                the afternoon.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">"Good evening!"</dialogue> said the
                <character>lad</character>. <dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"Good
                    evening!"</dialogue> said the <character>North Wind</character>. <dialogue
                        speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">"I want my rights for that meal of ours which you
                        took"</dialogue>, said the lad; <dialogue speaker="lad" subject="North Wind">"for, as
                            for that cloth I got, it isn’t worth a penny."</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"I’ve got no meal"</dialogue>, said the
                <character>North Wind</character>; <dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"but
                    yonder you have a ram which coins nothing but golden ducats as soon as you say to
                    it: ‘Rain, ram! make money!’"</dialogue></p>
            <p>So the <character>lad</character> thought this a fine thing; but as it was too far to get
                home that day, he turned in for the night to the same inn where he had slept before.</p>
            <p>Before he called for anything, he tried the truth of what the <character>North
                Wind</character> had said of the ram, and found it all right; but, when the
                <character>landlord</character> saw that, he thought it was a famous ram, and, when
                the <character>lad</character> had fallen asleep, he took another which couldn’t coin
                gold ducats, and changed the two.</p>
            <p>Next morning off went the <character>lad</character>; and when he got home to his
                <character>mother</character>, he said: <dialogue speaker="lad" subject="old widow"
                    >"After all, the <character>North Wind</character> is a jolly fellow; for now he has
                    given me a ram which can coin golden ducats if I only say ‘Ram, ram! make
                    money.’"</dialogue>
                <dialogue speaker="old widow" subject="lad">"All very true, I daresay"</dialogue>, said
                his <character>mother</character>; <dialogue speaker="old widow" subject="lad">"but I
                    shan’t believe any such stuff until I see the ducats made."</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="lad" subject="ram">"Ram, ram! make money!"</dialogue> said the
                <character>lad</character>; but if the Ram made anything, it wasn’t money. So the
                <character>lad</character> went back again to the <character>North Wind</character>,
                and <action actor="lad" subject="North Wind" sign = "negative">blew him up</action>, and said the ram was
                worth nothing, and he must have his rights for the meal.</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"Well!"</dialogue> said the <character>North
                Wind</character>; <dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="lad">"I’ve nothing else to
                    give you but that old stick in the corner yonder; but it’s a stick of that kind that
                    if you say: “‘Stick, stick! lay on!’ it lays on till you say: ‘Stick, stick! now
                    stop!’"</dialogue></p>
            <p>So, as the way was long, the <character>lad</character> turned in this night too to the
                <character>landlord</character>; but as he could pretty well guess how things stood
                as to the cloth and the ram, he lay down at once on the bench and began to <action
                    actor="lad" subject="environment" sign = "negative">snore</action>, as if he were asleep.</p>
            <p>Now the <character>landlord</character>, who easily saw that the stick must be worth
                something, <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="landlord" sign = "negative">hunted</descriptor> up one
                which was like it, and when he heard the lad snore, was going to change the two; but,
                just as the <character>landlord</character> was about to <action actor="landlord"
                    subject="stick" sign = "negative">take</action> it, the lad bawled out: <dialogue speaker="lad"
                        subject="stick">"Stick, stick! lay on!"</dialogue></p>
            <p>So the stick began to <action actor="stick" subject="landlord" sign = "negative">beat</action> the
                <character>landlord</character>, till he <action actor="landlord" subject="chair" sign = "negative"
                    >jumped</action> over chairs, and tables, and benches, and <action actor="landlord"
                        subject="environment" sign = "negative">yelled</action> and <action actor="landlord" subject="encironment" sign = "negative"
                            >roared</action>: <dialogue speaker="landlord" subject="lad">"Oh my! oh my! bid the
                                stick be still, else it will beat me to death, and you shall have back both your
                                cloth and our ram."</dialogue></p>
            <p>When the <character>lad</character> thought the <character>landlord</character> had got
                enough, he said: <dialogue speaker="lad" subject="stick">"Stick, stick! now
                    stop!"</dialogue></p>
            <p>Then he <action actor="lad" subject="cloth" sign = "positive">took</action> the cloth and put it into his
                pocket, and went home with his stick in his hand, <action actor="lad" subject="ram" sign = "negative"
                    >leading</action> the ram by a cord round its horns; and so he got his rights for
                the meal he had lost.</p>
        </body>
    </story>
    <story>
        <title>WHY THE SEA IS SALT</title>
        <body>
            <p>Once on a time, but it was a long, long time ago, there were two brothers, one
                <descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="Rich Brother" sign="Positive"
                    >rich</descriptor> and one <descriptor speaker="Narrartor" subject="Poor Brother"
                        sign="Negative">poor</descriptor>. Now, one Christmas eve, the poor one hadn’t so
                much as a crumb in the house, either of meat or bread, so he went to his brother to ask
                him for something to keep Christmas with, in God’s name. It was not the first time his
                brother had been forced to help him, and you may fancy he wasn’t very glad to see his
                face, but he said:</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother">“If you will do what I ask you to
                do, I’ll give you a whole flitch of bacon.”</dialogue> So the <character
                    who="Poor Brother">poor brother</character> said he would do anything, and was full
                of thanks.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother">“Well, here is the
                flitch”</dialogue>, said the <character who="Rich Brother">rich brother</character>,
                “and now go straight to Hell.”</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Rich Brother" speaker="Poor Brother">“What I have given my word to do,
                I must stick to”</dialogue>, said the other; so he took the flitch and set off. He
                walked the whole day, and at dusk he came to a place where he saw a very bright
                light.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Self" speaker="Poor Brother">“Maybe this is the place”</dialogue>,
                said the man to himself. So he turned aside, and the first thing he saw was an old,
                <character who="Old Man">old man</character>, with a long white beard, who stood in
                an outhouse, hewing wood for the Christmas fire. </p>
            <p>
                <dialogue subject="Old Man" speaker="Poor Brother">“Good even”</dialogue>, said the man
                with the flitch.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Old Man">“The same to you; whither are you
                going so late?”</dialogue> said the man.</p>
            <p>
                <dialogue subject="Old Man" speaker="Poor Brother">“Oh! I’m going to Hell, if I only
                    knew the right way”</dialogue>, answered the poor man.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Old Man">“Well, you’re not far wrong, for this
                is Hell”</dialogue>, said the old man; <dialogue subject="Poor Brother"
                    speaker="Old Man">“when you get inside they will be all for buying your flitch, for
                    meat is scarce in Hell; but mind, you don’t sell it unless you get the hand-quern
                    which stands behind the door for it. When you come out, I’ll <action actor="Old Man"
                        subject="Poor Brother" sign="Neutral"> teach</action> you how to handle the
                    quern, for it’s good to grind almost anything.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>So the man with the flitch <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Old Man" sign="Positive"
                >thanked</action> the other for his good advice, and gave a great knock at the
                <character who="Devil">Devil</character>’s door.</p>
            <p> When he got in, everything went just as the old man had said. All the devils, great and
                small, came swarming up to him like ants round an anthill, and each tried to outbid the
                other for the flitch. </p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Devil" speaker="Poor Brother">“Well!”</dialogue> said the man,
                <dialogue subject="Devil" speaker="Poor Brother"> "by rights my old dame and I ought
                    to have this flitch for our Christmas dinner; but since you have all set your hearts
                    on it, I suppose I must give it up to you; but if I sell it at all, I’ll have for it
                    that quern behind the door yonder.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>At first the <character who="Devil">Devil</character> wouldn’t hear of such a bargain,
                and <action actor="Devil" subject="Poor Brother" sign="Neutral">chaffered and
                    haggled</action> with the man; but he stuck to what he said, and at last the
                <character who="Devil">Devil</character> had to part with his quern. When the man
                got out into the yard, he asked the old woodcutter how he was to handle the quern; and
                after he had learned how to use it, he <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Old Man"
                    sign="Positive">thanked</action> the old man and went off home as fast as he could,
                but still the clock had struck twelve on Christmas eve before he reached his own
                door.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Poor Brother's Wife">“Wherever in the world
                have you been?”</dialogue> said his <character who="Poor Brother's Wife">old
                    dame</character>, <dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Poor Brother's Wife"
                        >“here have I sat hour after hour <action actor="Poor Brother's Wife"
                            subject="Poor Brother" sign="Positive">waiting</action> and watching, without so
                        much as two sticks to lay together under the Christmas brose.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>
                <dialogue subject="Poor Brother's Wife" speaker="Poor Brother">“Oh!”</dialogue> said the
                man, <dialogue subject="Poor Brother's Wife" speaker="Poor Brother">“I couldn’t get back
                    before, for I had to go a long way first for one thing, and then for another; but
                    now you shall see what you shall see.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>So he put the quern on the table, and bade it first of all grind lights, then a
                table-cloth, then meat, then ale, and so on till they had got everything that was nice
                for Christmas fare. He had only to speak the word, and the quern ground out what he
                wanted. The old dame stood by blessing her stars, and kept on asking where he had got
                this wonderful quern, but he wouldn’t tell her.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother's Wife" speaker="Poor Brother">“It’s all one where I got
                it from; you see the quern is a good one, and the mill-stream never freezes, that’s
                enough.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>So he ground meat and drink and dainties enough to last out till Twelfth Day, and on the
                third day he asked all his friends and kin to his house, and gave a great feast. Now,
                when his <character who="Rich Brother">rich brother</character> saw all that was on the
                table, and all that was behind in the larder, he grew quite <descriptor
                    subject="Rich Brother" speaker="Narrator" sign="Negative">spiteful and
                    wild</descriptor>, for he <action actor="Rich Brother" subject="Poor Brother"
                        sign="Negative">couldn’t bear that his brother should have anything.</action></p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Party" speaker="Rich Brother">“’Twas only on Christmas
                eve”</dialogue>, he said to the rest, <dialogue subject="Party" speaker="Rich Brother"
                    >“he was <descriptor subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother" sign="Negative"
                        >in such straits</descriptor>, that he came and asked for a morsel of food in
                    God’s name, and now he gives a feast <descriptor speaker="Rich Brother"
                        subject="Poor Brother" sign="Negative">as if he were count or
                        king</descriptor>”</dialogue>; and he turned to his brother and said:</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother">“But whence, in Hell’s name, have
                you got all this wealth?”</dialogue></p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Rich Brother" speaker="Poor Brother">“From behind the
                door”</dialogue>, answered the <character who="Poor Brother">owner of the
                    quern</character>, for he didn’t care to <fig_lang type="Metaphor" subject="Quern"
                        relation="Revealing Secret" sign="Negative">let the cat out of the bag</fig_lang>.
                But later on the evening, when he had got a drop too much, he could keep his secret no
                longer, and brought out the quern and said:</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Party" speaker="Poor Brother">“There, you see what has gotten me all
                this wealth”</dialogue>; and so he made the quern grind all kind of things. When his
                <character who="Rich Brother">brother</character> saw it, he set his heart on having
                the quern, and, after a deal of <action actor="Rich Brother" subject="Poor Brother"
                    sign="Neutral">coaxing</action>, he got it; but he had to pay three hundred dollars
                for it, and <character who="Poor Brother">his brother</character> bargained to keep it
                till hay-harvest, for he thought, if I keep it till then, I can make it grind meat and
                drink that will last for years. So you may fancy the quern didn’t grow rusty for want of
                work, and when hay-harvest came, the <character who="Rich Brother">rich
                    brother</character> got it, but <character who="Poor Brother">the other</character>
                took care <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Rich Brother" sign="Negative">not to
                    teach</action> him how to handle it. </p>
            <p>It was evening when the <character who="Rich Brother">rich brother</character> got the
                quern home, and next morning he told his wife to go out into the hay-field and toss,
                while the mowers cut the grass, and he would stay at home and get the dinner ready. So,
                when dinner-time drew near, he put the quern on the kitchen table and said:</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Self" speaker="Rich Brother">“Grind herrings and broth, and grind them
                good and fast.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>So the quern began to grind herrings and broth; first of all, all the dishes full, then
                all the tubs full, and so on till the kitchen floor was quite covered. Then the man
                <action subject="Quern" actor="Rich Brother" sign="Negative">twisted and
                    twirled</action> at the quern to get it to stop, but for all his twisting and
                fingering the quern went on grinding, and in a little while the broth rose so high that
                <character who="Rich Brother">the man</character> was like to drown. So he threw
                open the kitchen door and ran into the parlour, but it wasn’t long before the quern had
                ground the parlour full too, and it was only at the risk of his life that the man could
                get hold of the latch of the house door through the stream of broth. When he got the
                door open, he ran out and set off down the road, with the stream of herrings and broth
                at his heels, roaring like a waterfall over the whole farm. Now, <character
                    who="Rich Brother's Wife">his old dame</character>, who was in the field tossing
                hay, thought it a long time to dinner, and at last she said:</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Fieldworkers" speaker="Rich Brother's Wife">“Well! though <character
                who="Rich Brother">the master</character> doesn’t call us home, we may as well
                go. Maybe he finds it hard work to boil the broth, and will be glad of my
                help.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>The men were willing enough, so they sauntered homewards; but just as they had got a
                little way up the hill, what should they meet but herrings, and broth, and bread, all
                running and dashing, and splashing together in a stream, and the master himself <action
                    actor="Rich Brother" subject="Self" sign="Negative">running before them for his
                    life</action>, and as he passed them he bawled out:</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Rich Brother" subject="Fieldworkers">“Would to heaven each of you had
                a hundred throats! but take care you’re not drowned in the broth.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>Away he went, as though the <character who="Devil">Evil One</character> were at his
                heels, to <character who="Poor Brother">his brother</character>’s house, and begged him
                for God’s sake to take back the quern that instant; for, said he:</p>
            <p><dialogue speaker="Rich Brother" subject="Poor Brother">“If it grinds only one hour more,
                the whole parish will be swallowed up by herrings and broth.”</dialogue>
            </p>
            <p>But <character who="Poor Brother">his brother</character>
                <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Rich Brother" sign="Negative">wouldn’t hear of
                    taking it back</action> till the other paid him down three hundred dollars more.</p>
            <p>So the<character who="Poor Brother">poor brother</character> got both the money and the
                quern, and it wasn’t long before he <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Rich Brother"
                    sign="Negative">set up a farm-house far finer than the one in which his brother
                    lived</action>, and with the quern he ground so much gold that he covered it with
                plates of gold; and as the farm lay by the sea-side, the golden house gleamed and
                glistened far away over the sea. <transformation subject="Poor Brother" form="Rich Man">All who sailed by put ashore to see the <character
                    who="Poor Brother">rich man</character> in the golden house</transformation>, and to see the
                wonderful quern, the fame of which spread far and wide, till there was nobody who hadn’t
                heard tell of it.</p>
            <p>So one day there came a <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> who wanted to see
                the quern; and the first thing he <action subject="Poor Brother" actor="Skipper"
                    sign="Neutral">asked</action> was if it could grind salt.</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Skipper" speaker="Poor Brother">“Grind salt!”</dialogue> said
                <character who="Poor Brother">the owner</character>; <dialogue subject="Skipper"
                    speaker="Poor Brother">“I should just think it could. It can grind
                    anything.”</dialogue> When the <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> heard
                that, he said he must have the quern, cost what it would; for if he only had it, he
                thought he should be rid of his long voyages across stormy seas for a lading of salt.
                Well, at first <character who="Poor Brother">the man</character> wouldn’t hear of
                parting with the quern; but the <character who="Skipper">skipper</character>
                <action actor="Skipper" subject="Poor Brother" sign="Neutral">begged and prayed</action>
                so hard, that at last he let him have it, but he had to pay many, many thousand dollars
                for it. Now, when the <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> had got the quern on
                his back, he soon made off with it, for he was <action actor="Skipper"
                    subject="Poor Brother" sign="Negative">afraid lest the man should change his
                    mind</action>; so he had no time to ask how to handle the quern, but got on board
                his ship as fast as he could, and set sail. When he had sailed a good way off, he
                brought the quern on deck and said:</p>
            <p><dialogue subject="Self" speaker="Skipper">“Grind salt, and grind both good and
                fast.”</dialogue></p>
            <p>Well, the quern began to grind salt so that it poured out like water; and when the
                <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> had got the ship full, he wished to
                stop the quern, but whichever way he turned it, and however much he tried, it was no
                good; the quern kept grinding on, and the heap of salt grew higher and higher, and at
                last down sank the ship. </p>
            <p>There lies the quern at the bottom of the sea, and grinds away at this very day, and
                that’s why the sea is salt.</p>
        </body>
    </story>
</tales>
