<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- In this story, the Prince is bewitched, meaning he tranforms not through his own will, but through the work of someone else. Consider 
    this for analysis? Maybe add an attribute to transformation such as @will, which can be either "self" or "other"-->
<?xml-model href="norseTalesSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <title>EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time there was a poor <character>husbandman</character> who had so many
            children that he hadn’t much of either food or clothing to give them. Pretty children
            they all were, but the prettiest was the <character>youngest daughter</character>, who
            was so <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Princess" sign="positive">lovely there
                was no end to her loveliness.</descriptor></p>
        <p>So one day, ’twas on a Thursday evening late at the fall of the year, the weather was so
            wild and rough outside, and it was so cruelly dark, and rain fell and wind blew, till
            the walls of the cottage shook again. There they all sat round the fire busy with this
            thing and that. But just then, all at once something gave three taps on the window-pane.
            Then the <character>father</character> went out to see what was the matter; and, when he
            got out of doors, what should he see but a <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="White Bear" sign="positive">great big</descriptor>
            <character>White Bear.</character></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="father">“Good evening to you!”</dialogue> said
            the White Bear. <dialogue speaker="father" subject="White Bear">“The same to
                you”</dialogue>, said the man. <dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="father">“Will
                you give me your youngest daughter? If you will, I’ll make you as rich as you are
                now poor”</dialogue>, said the Bear.</p>
        <p>Well, <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="father" sign="negative">the man would not
                be at all sorry to be so rich</descriptor>; but still he thought he must have a bit
            of a talk with his daughter first; so he went in and told them how there was a
                <descriptor speaker="father" subject="White Bear" sign="positive">great</descriptor>
            <character>White Bear</character> waiting outside, who had given his word to make them
            so rich if he could only have the youngest daughter.</p>
        <p>The lassie said <dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="father">“No!”</dialogue> outright.
            Nothing could get her to say anything else; so the man went out and settled it with the
                <character>White Bear</character>, that he should come again the next Thursday
            evening and get an answer. Meantime he talked his daughter over, and kept on telling her
            of all the riches they would get, and how well off she would be herself; and so at last
            she thought better of it, and <action actor="daughter" subject="rags" sign="positive"
                >washed</action> and <action actor="daughter" subject="rags" sign="positive"
                >mended</action> her rags, made herself as smart as she could, and was ready to
            start. I can’t say her packing gave her much trouble.</p>
        <p>Next Thursday evening came the <character>White Bear</character> to <action
                actor="White Bear" subject="daughter" sign="negative">fetch</action> her, and she
            got upon his back with her bundle, and off they went. So, when they had gone a bit of
            the way, the White Bear said: <dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“Are you
                afraid?”</dialogue>
            <dialogue speaker="Priness" subject="White Bear">“No! she wasn’t.”</dialogue>
            <dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“Well! mind and hold tight by my
                shaggy coat, and then there’s nothing to fear”</dialogue>, said the Bear.</p>
        <p>So she rode a long, long way, till they came to a great steep hill. There, on the face
            of it, the <character>White Bear</character> gave a knock, and a door opened, and they
            came into a castle, where there were many rooms all lit up; rooms gleaming with silver
            and gold; and there too was a table ready laid, and it was all as grand as grand could
            be. Then the <character>White Bear</character>
            <action actor="White Bear" subject="daughter" sign="positive">gave</action> her a silver
            bell; and when she wanted anything, she was only to ring it, and she would get it at
            once.</p>
        <p>Well, after she had eaten and drunk, and evening wore on, she got sleepy after her
            journey, and thought she would like to go to bed, so she <action actor="daughter"
                subject="bell" sign="positive">rang</action> the bell; and she had scarce taken hold
            of it before she came into a chamber, where there was a bed made, as fair and white as
            any one would wish to sleep in, with silken pillows and curtains, and gold fringe. All
            that was in the room was gold or silver; but when she had gone to bed, and put out the
            light, a <character>man</character> came and laid himself alongside her. <transformation
                form="man" subject="White Bear">That was the White Bear, who threw off his beast
                shape at night</transformation>; but she never saw him, for he always came after she
            had put out the light, and before the day dawned he was up and off again. So things went
            on happily for a while, but at last she began to get <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="daughter" sign="negative">silent</descriptor> and <descriptor
                speaker="narrator" subject="daughter" sign="negative">sorrowful</descriptor>; for
            there she went about all day alone, and she longed to go home to see her father and
            mother and brothers and sisters. So one day, when the <character>White Bear</character>
            asked what it was that she lacked, she said it was so dull and lonely there, and how she
            longed to go home to see her father and mother, and brothers and sisters, and that was
            why she was so sad and sorrowful, because she couldn’t get to them.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“Well, well!”</dialogue> said the
            Bear, <dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“perhaps there’s a cure for all
                this; but you must promise me one thing, not to talk alone with your mother, but
                only when the rest are by to hear; for she’ll take you by the hand and try to lead
                you into a room alone to talk; but you must mind and not do that, else you’ll bring
                bad luck on both of us.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So one Sunday the <character>White Bear</character> came and said now they could set off
            to see her father and mother. Well, off they started, she sitting on his back; and they
            went far and long. At last they came to a grand house, and there her brothers and
            sisters were running about out of doors at play, and everything was so <descriptor
                speaker="narrator" subject="family" sign="positive">pretty</descriptor>, ’twas a joy
            to see.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“This is where your father and mother
                live now”</dialogue>, said the White Bear; <dialogue speaker="White Bear"
                subject="daughter">“but don’t forget what I told you, else you’ll make us both
                unlucky.”</dialogue>
            <dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="self">“No! bless her, she’d not
                forget”</dialogue>; and when she had reached the house, the <character>White
                Bear</character> turned right about and left her.</p>
        <p>Then when she went in to see her father and mother, there was such <descriptor
                speaker="narrator" subject="father and mother" sign="positive">joy</descriptor>,
            there was no end to it. None of them thought they could thank her enough for all she had
            done for them. Now, they had everything they wished, as good as good could be, and they
            all wanted to know how she got on where she lived.</p>
        <p>Well, she said, it was very good to live where she did; she had all she wished. What she
            said beside I don’t know; but I don’t think any of them had the right end of the stick,
            or that they got much out of her. But so in the afternoon, after they had done dinner,
            all happened as the <character>White Bear</character> had said. Her mother wanted to
            talk with her alone in her bed-room; but she minded what the <character>White
                Bear</character> had said, and <action actor="daughter" subject="environment"
                sign="negative">wouldn’t go</action> upstairs.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="mother">“Oh! what we have to talk about, will
                keep”</dialogue>, she said, and put her mother off. But some how or other, her
            mother got round her at last, and she had to tell her the whole story. So she said, how
            every night, when she had gone to bed, a <character>man</character> came and <action
                actor="Prince" subject="daughter" sign="positive">lay</action> down beside her as
            soon as she had put out the light, and how she never saw him, because he was always up
            and away before the morning dawned; and how she went about <descriptor
                speaker="daughter" subject="Princess" sign="negative">woeful</descriptor> and
            sorrowing, for she thought she should so like to see him, and how all day long she
            walked about there alone, and how <descriptor speaker="daughter" subject="daughter"
                sign="negative">dull</descriptor>, and <descriptor speaker="daughter"
                subject="daughter" sign="negative">dreary</descriptor>, and lonesome it was.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="mother" subject="daughter">“My!”</dialogue> said her mother;
                <dialogue speaker="mother" subject="daughter">“it may well be a
                    <character>Troll</character> you slept with! But now I’ll teach you a lesson how
                to set eyes on him. I’ll give you a bit of candle, which you can carry home in your
                bosom; just light that while he is asleep, but take care not to drop the tallow on
                him.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Yes! she took the candle, and hid it in her bosom, and as night drew on, the
                <character>White Bear</character> came and <action actor="White Bear"
                subject="daughter" sign="negative">fetched</action> her away. But when they had gone
            a bit of the way, the <character>White Bear</character> asked if all hadn’t happened as
            he had said? <dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="White Bear">“Well, she couldn’t say
                it hadn’t.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“Now, mind”</dialogue>, said he,
                <dialogue speaker="White Bear" subject="daughter">“if you have listened to your
                mother’s advice, you have brought bad luck on us both, and then, all that has passed
                between us will be as nothing.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="White Bear">“No”</dialogue>, she said, <dialogue
                speaker="daughter" subject="White Bear">“she hadn’t listened to her mother’s
                advice.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So when she reached home, and had gone to bed, it was the old story over again. There
            came a <character>man</character> and lay down beside her; but at dead of night, when
            she heard he slept, she got up and struck a light, <action actor="daughter"
                subject="candle" sign="positive">lit</action> the candle, and let the light shine on
            him, and so she saw that he was the <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Prince"
                sign="positive">loveliest</descriptor>
            <character>Prince</character> one ever set eyes on, and she fell so deep in love with
            him on the spot, that she thought she couldn’t live if she didn’t give him a kiss there
            and then. And so she did, but as she <action actor="daughter" subject="Prince"
                sign="positive">kissed</action> him, she dropped three hot drops of tallow on his
            shirt, and he woke up.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“What have you done?”</dialogue> he cried;
                <dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“now you have made us both unlucky,
                for had you held out only this one year, I had been freed. For I have a
                    <character>stepmother</character> who has <action actor="stepmother"
                    subject="Prince" sign="negative">bewitched</action> me, so that I am a White
                Bear by day, and a Man by night. But now all ties are snapt between us; now I must
                set off from you to her. She lives in a Castle which stands EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST
                O’ THE MOON, and there, too, is a <character>Princess</character>, with a
                    <descriptor speaker="Prince" subject="Princess" sign="negative">nose three ells
                    long</descriptor>, and she’s the wife I must have now.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>She <action actor="daughter" subject="self" sign="negative">wept</action> and took it
            ill, but there was no help for it; go he must. Then she asked if she mightn’t go with
            him? No, she mightn’t. <dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="Prince">“Tell me the way,
                then”</dialogue>, she said, <dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="Prince">“and I’ll
                search you out; that surely I may get leave to do.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“Yes, she might do that”</dialogue>, he
            said; <dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“but there was no way to that place.
                It lay EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON, and thither she’d never find her
                way.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So next morning, when she woke up, both <character>Prince</character> and castle were
            gone, and then she lay on a little green patch, in the midst of the gloomy thick wood,
            and by her side lay the same bundle of rags she had brought with her from her old home.</p>
        <p>So when she had rubbed the sleep out of her eyes, and <action actor="Princess"
                subject="self" sign="negative">wept</action> till she was tired, she <action
                actor="daughter" subject="self" sign="positive">set out</action> on her way, and
            walked many, many days, till she came to a lofty crag. Under it sat an <character>old
                hag</character>, and played with a gold apple which she tossed about. Her the lassie
            asked if she knew the way to the <character>Prince</character>, who lived with his
            step-mother in the Castle, that lay EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON, and who was to
            marry the <character>Princess</character>
            <descriptor speaker="daughter" subject="Princess" sign="negative">with a nose three ells
                long</descriptor>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old hag" subject="daughter">“How did you come to know about
                him?”</dialogue> asked the old hag; <dialogue speaker="old hag" subject="daughter"
                >“but maybe you are the lassie who ought to have had him?”</dialogue> Yes, she was.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old hag" subject="daughter">“So, so; it’s you, is it?”</dialogue>
            said the old hag. <dialogue speaker="old hag" subject="daughter">“Well, all I know about
                him is, that he lives in the castle that lies EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON,
                and thither you’ll come, late or never; but still you may have the loan of my horse,
                and on him you can ride to my next neighbour. Maybe she’ll be able to tell you; and
                when you get there, just give the horse a switch under the left ear, and beg him to
                be off home; and, stay, this gold apple you may take with you.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So she got upon the horse, and <action actor="daughter" subject="horse" sign="positive"
                >rode</action> a long long time, till she came to another crag, under which sat
                <character>another old hag</character>, with a gold carding-comb. Her the lassie
            asked if she knew the way to the castle that lay EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON,
            and she answered, like the first old hag, that she knew nothing about it, except it was
            east o’ the sun and west o’ the moon.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="second old hag" subject="daughter">“And thither you’ll come, late or
                never, but you shall have the loan of my horse to my next neighbour; maybe she’ll
                tell you all about it; and when you get there, just switch the horse under the left
                ear, and beg him to be off home.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>And this <character>old hag</character> gave her the golden carding-comb; it might be
            she’d find some use for it, she said. So the lassie got up on the horse, and rode a far
            far way, and a weary time; and so at last she came to another great crag, under which
            sat <character>another old hag</character>, spinning with a golden spinning-wheel. Her,
            too, she asked if she knew the way to the Prince, and where the castle was that lay EAST
            O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON. So it was the same thing over again.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="third old hag" subject="daughter">“Maybe it’s you who ought to have
                had the Prince?”</dialogue> said the old hag. Yes, it was.</p>
        <p>But she, too, didn’t know the way a bit better than the other two. “<dialogue
                speaker="third old hag" subject="daughter">East o’ the sun and west o’ the moon it
                was”</dialogue>, she knew—that was all.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="third old hag" subject="daughter">“And thither you’ll come, late or
                never; but I’ll lend you my horse, and then I think you’d best ride to the
                    <character>East Wind</character> and ask him; maybe, he knows those parts, and
                can blow you thither. But when you get to him, you need only give the horse a switch
                under the left ear, and he’ll trot home of himself.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>And so, too, she gave her the gold spinning-wheel. <dialogue speaker="third old hag"
                subject="daughter">“Maybe you’ll find a use for it”</dialogue>, said the old hag.</p>
        <p>Then on she <action actor="daughter" subject="horse" sign="positive">rode</action> many
            many days, a weary time, before she got to the <character>East Wind</character>’s house,
            but at last she did reach it, and then she asked the <character>East Wind</character> if
            he could tell her the way to the Prince who dwelt east o’ the sun and west o’ the moon.
            Yes, the <character>East Wind</character> had often heard tell of it, the
                <character>Prince</character> and the castle, but he couldn’t tell the way, for he
            had never blown so far.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="East Wind" subject="daughter">“But, if you will, I’ll go with you to
                my brother the <character>West Wind</character>, maybe he knows, for he’s much
                    <descriptor speaker="East Wind" subject="West Wind" sign="positive"
                    >stronger</descriptor>. So, if you will just get on my back, I’ll carry you
                thither.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Yes, she got on his back, and I should just think they <action actor="East Wind"
                subject="daughter" sign="positive">went briskly</action> along.</p>
        <p>So when they got there, they went into the <character>West Wind</character>’s house, and
            the <character>East Wind</character> said the lassie he had brought was the one who
            ought to have had the <character>Prince</character> who lived in the castle EAST O’ THE
            SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON; and so she had set out to seek him, and how he had come with
            her, and would be glad to know if the <character>West Wind</character> knew how to get
            to the castle.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="West Wind" subject="East Wind">“Nay”</dialogue>, said the West Wind,
                <dialogue speaker="West Wind" subject="East Wind">“so far I’ve never blown; but if
                you will, I’ll go with you to our brother the <character>South Wind</character>, for
                he’s much stronger than either of us, and he has flapped his wings far and wide.
                Maybe he’ll tell you. You can get on my back, and I’ll carry you to him.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Yes! she got on his back, and so they <action actor="West Wind" subject="daughter"
                sign="positive">travelled</action> to the <character>South Wind</character>, and
            weren’t so very long on the way, I should think.</p>
        <p>When they got there, the <character>West Wind</character> asked him if he could tell her
            the way to the castle that lay EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON, for it was she who
            ought to have had the prince who lived there.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="South Wind" subject="West Wind">“You don’t say so! That’s she, is
                it?”</dialogue> said the South Wind.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="South Wind" subject="West Wind">“Well, I have blustered about in most
                places in my time, but so far have I never blown; but if you will, I’ll take you to
                my brother the <character>North Wind</character>; he is the <descriptor
                    speaker="South Wind" subject="North Wind" sign="positive">oldest</descriptor>
                and <descriptor speaker="South Wind" subject="North Wind" sign="positive"
                    >strongest</descriptor> of the whole lot of us, and if he don’t know where it
                is, you’ll never find any one in the world to tell you. You can get on my back, and
                I’ll carry you thither.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Yes! she got on his back, and away he <action actor="South Wind" subject="daughter"
                sign="positive">went from his house</action> at a fine rate. And this time, too, she
            wasn’t long on her way.</p>
        <p>So when they got to the <character>North Wind</character>’s house, he was so <descriptor
                speaker="narrator" subject="North Wind" sign="negative">wild</descriptor> and
                <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="North Wind" sign="negative"
                >cross</descriptor>, cold puffs came from him a long way off.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="South Wind">“BLAST YOU BOTH, WHAT DO YOU
                WANT?”</dialogue> he roared out to them ever so far off, so that it <action
                actor="North Wind" subject="South Wind" sign="negative">struck</action> them with an
            icy shiver.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="South Wind" subject="North Wind">“Well”</dialogue>, said the South
            Wind, <dialogue speaker="South Wind" subject="North Wind">“you needn’t be so
                foul-mouthed, for here I am, your brother, the <character>South Wind</character>,
                and here is the <character>lassie</character> who ought to have had the
                    <character>Prince</character> who dwells in the castle that lies EAST O’ THE SUN
                AND WEST O’ THE MOON, and now she wants to ask you if you ever were there, and can
                tell her the way, for she would be so glad to find him again.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="South Wind">“YES, I KNOW WELL ENOUGH WHERE IT
                IS”</dialogue>, said the North Wind; <dialogue speaker="North Wind"
                subject="South Wind">“once in my life I blew an aspen-leaf thither, but I was so
                tired I couldn’t blow a puff for ever so many days after. But if you really wish to
                go thither, and aren’t afraid to come along with me, I’ll take you on my back and
                see if I can blow you thither.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Yes! <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="daughter" sign="positive">with all her
                heart</descriptor>; she must and would get thither if it were possible in any way;
            and as for fear, however madly he went, she wouldn’t be at all afraid.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="South Wind">“Very well, then”</dialogue>, said
            the North Wind, <dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="South Wind">“but you must sleep
                here to-night, for we must have the whole day before us, if we’re to get thither at
                all.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Early next morning the <character>North Wind</character> woke her, and puffed himself
            up, and blew himself out, and made himself so <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="North Wind" sign="positive">stout</descriptor> and big, ’<descriptor
                speaker="narrator" subject="North Wind" sign="negative">twas gruesome to look at
                him</descriptor>; and so off they went high up through the air, as if they would
            never stop till they got to the world’s end.</p>
        <p>Down here below there was such a storm; it threw down long tracts of wood and many
            houses, and when it swept over the great sea, ships foundered by hundreds.</p>
        <p>So they tore on and on—no one can believe how far they went—and all the while they still
            went over the sea, and the <character>North Wind</character> got more and more weary,
            and so out of breath he could scarce bring out a puff, and his wings drooped and
            drooped, till at last he sunk so low that the crests of the waves dashed over his heels.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="North Wind" subject="daughter">“Are you afraid?”</dialogue> said the
            North Wind. <dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="North Wind">“No!”</dialogue> she
            wasn’t.</p>
        <p>But they weren’t very far from land; and the <character>North Wind</character> had still
            so much strength left in him that he managed to <action actor="North Wind"
                subject="daughter" sign="positive">throw</action> her up on the shore under the
            windows of the castle which lay EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON; but then he was so
            weak and worn out, he had to stay there and rest many days before he could get home
            again.</p>
        <p>Next morning the <character>lassie</character> sat down under the castle window, and
            began to play with the gold apple; and the first person she saw was the
                <character>Long-nose</character> who was to have the <character>Prince</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="daughter">“What do you want for your gold apple,
                you lassie?”</dialogue> said the Long-nose, and threw up the window. <dialogue
                speaker="daughter" subject="Princess">“It’s not for sale, for gold or
                money”</dialogue>, said the lassie.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="daughter">“If it’s not for sale for gold or money,
                what is it that you will sell it for? You may name your own price”</dialogue>, said
            the Princess.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="daughter" subject="Princess">“Well! if I may get to the
                    <character>Prince</character>, who lives here, and be with him to-night, you
                shall have it”</dialogue>, said the lassie whom the North Wind had brought.</p>
        <p>Yes! she might; that could be done. So the <character>Princess</character> got the gold
            apple; but when the <character>lassie</character> came up to the Prince’s bed-room at
            night he was fast asleep; she called him and <action actor="daughter" subject="Prince"
                sign="positive">shook</action> him, and between whiles she wept sore; but all she
            could do she couldn’t wake him up. Next morning as soon as day broke, came the
                <character>Princess</character> with the long nose, and drove her out again.</p>
        <p>So in the daytime she sat down under the castle windows and began to card with her
            carding-comb, and the same thing happened. The <character>Princess</character> asked
            what she wanted for it; and she said it wasn’t for sale for gold or money, but if she
            might get leave to go up to the <character>Prince</character> and be with him that
            night, the <character>Princess</character> should have it. But when she went up she
            found him fast asleep again, and all she called, and all she <action actor="daughter"
                subject="Prince" sign="positive">shook</action>, and <action actor="daughter"
                subject="Prince" sign="negative">wept</action>, and prayed, she couldn’t get life
            into him; and as soon as the first gray peep of day came, then came the
                <character>Princess</character> with the long nose, and chased her out again.</p>
        <p>So, in the day time, the <character>lassie</character> sat down outside under the castle
            window, and began to spin with her golden spinning-wheel, and that, too, the
                <character>Princess</character> with the long nose wanted to have. So she threw up
            the window and asked what she wanted for it. The <character>lassie</character> said, as
            she had said twice before, it wasn’t for sale for gold or money; but if she might go up
            to the Prince who was there, and be with him alone that night, she might have it.</p>
        <p>Yes! she might do that and welcome. But now you must know there were some
                <character>Christian folk</character> who had been carried off thither, and as they
            sat in their room, which was next the <character>Prince</character>, they had heard how
            a woman had been in there, and wept and prayed, and called to him two nights running,
            and they told that to the <character>Prince</character>.</p>
        <p>That evening, when the <character>Princess</character> came with her sleepy drink, the
                <character>Prince</character> made as if he drank, but <action actor="Prince"
                subject="drink" sign="positive">threw</action> it over his shoulder, for he could
            guess it was a sleepy drink. So, when the <character>lassie</character> came in, she
            found the <character>Prince</character> wide awake; and then she told him the whole
            story how she had come thither.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“Ah”</dialogue>, said the Prince,
                <dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“you’ve just come in the very nick of
                time, for to-morrow is to be our wedding-day; but now I won’t have the
                    <character>Long-nose</character>, and you are the only woman in the world who
                can set me free. I’ll say I want to see what my wife is fit for, and beg her to wash
                the shirt which has the three spots of tallow on it; she’ll say yes, for she doesn’t
                know ’tis you who put them there; but that’s a work only for <character>Christian
                    folk</character>, and not for <descriptor speaker="Prince" subject="Trolls"
                    sign="negative">such a pack of</descriptor>
                <character>Trolls</character>, and so I’ll say that I won’t have any other for my
                bride than the woman who can wash them out, and ask you to do it.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So there was great <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="daughter" sign="positive"
                >joy</descriptor> and <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Prince"
                sign="positive">love</descriptor> between them all that night. But next day, when
            the wedding was to be, the Prince said: <dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="step mother"
                >“First of all, I’d like to see what my bride is fit for.”</dialogue>
            <dialogue speaker="step mother" subject="Prince">“Yes!”</dialogue> said the step-mother,
            with all her heart.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="step mother">“Well”</dialogue>, said the Prince,
                <dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="step mother">“I’ve got a fine shirt which I’d
                like for my wedding shirt, but some how or other it has got three spots of tallow on
                it, which I must have washed out; and I have sworn never to take any other bride
                than the woman who’s able to do that. If she can’t, she’s not worth
                having.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Well, that was no great thing they said, so they agreed, and she with the long-nose
            began to wash away as hard as she could, but the more she rubbed and scrubbed, the
            bigger the spots grew.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="step mother" subject="Princess">“Ah!”</dialogue> said the old hag,
            her mother, <dialogue speaker="step mother" subject="Princess">“you can’t wash; let me
                try.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>But she hadn’t long taken the shirt in hand, before it got far worse than ever, and with
            all her rubbing, and wringing, and scrubbing, the spots grew bigger and blacker, and the
            darker and uglier was the shirt.</p>
        <p>Then all the other <character>Trolls</character> began to wash, but the longer it
            lasted, the blacker and uglier the shirt grew, till at last it was as black all over as
            if it had been up the chimney.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Trolls">“Ah!”</dialogue> said the Prince, <dialogue
                speaker="Prince" subject="Trolls">“you’re none of you worth a straw you can’t wash.
                Why there, outside, sits a beggar <character>lassie</character>, I’ll be bound she
                knows how to wash better than the whole lot of you. COME IN LASSIE!”</dialogue> he
            shouted.</p>
        <p>Well, in she came. <dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“Can you wash this
                shirt clean, lassie, you?”</dialogue> said he. <dialogue speaker="daughter"
                subject="Prince">“I don’t know”</dialogue>, she said, <dialogue speaker="daughter"
                subject="Prince">“but I think I can.”</dialogue> And almost before she had taken it
            and dipped it in the water, it was as white as driven snow, and whiter still. <dialogue
                speaker="Prince" subject="daughter">“Yes; you are the <character>lassie</character>
                for me”</dialogue>, said the Prince.</p>
        <p>At that the old hag <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="step mother" sign="negative"
                >flew into such a rage</descriptor>, she burst on the spot, and the
                <character>Princess</character>
            <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Princess" sign="negative">with the long
                nose</descriptor> after her, and the whole pack of <character>Trolls</character>
            after her—at least I’ve never heard a word about them since.</p>
        <p>As for the <character>Prince</character> and <character>Princess</character>, they set
            free all the poor <character>Christian folk</character> who had been carried off and
            shut up there; and they took with them all the silver and gold, and flitted away as far
            as they could from the Castle that lay EAST O’ THE SUN AND WEST O’ THE MOON.</p>
    </body>
</story>
