<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="norseTalesSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <title>TATTERHOOD</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time there was a <character who="King Queen">king and a queen</character>
            <descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="King Queen" sign="neutral">who had no
                children</descriptor>, <descriptor subject="Queen" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">and that gave the queen much grief; she scarce had one happy
                hour. She was always bewailing and bemoaning herself, and saying how dull and
                lonesome it was in the palace.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="herself">“If we had children there’d be life enough”,
                she said.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Wherever she went in all her realm she found God’s blessing in children, even in the
            vilest hut; and wherever she came she heard the Goodies scolding the bairns, and saying
            how they had done that and that wrong. All this the queen heard, and thought it would be
            so nice to do as other women did. <action actor="King Queen" subject="adopted daughter"
                sign="positive">At last the <character who="King Queen">king and queen</character>
                took into their palace a stranger <character who="adopted daughter"
                    >lassie</character> to rear up, that they might have her always with them, to
                love her if she did well, and scold her if she did wrong, like their own
                child.</action></p>
        <p>So one day the <character who="adopted daughter">little lassie</character> whom they had
            taken as their own, ran down into the palace yard, and was playing with a gold apple.
            Just then an <character who="old beggar wife">old beggar wife</character> came by, who
            had a <character who="beggar wife's daughter">little girl</character> with her, and it
            wasn’t long before the <character who="adopted daughter">little lassie</character> and
            the <character who="beggar wife's daughter">beggar’s bairn</character> were great
            friends, and began to play together, and to toss the gold apple about between them.
                <action actor="Queen" subject="adopted daughter" sign="neutral">When the <character
                    who="Queen">Queen</character> saw this, as she sat at a window in the palace,
                she tapped on the pane for her foster-daughter to come up.</action> She went at
            once, but the beggar-girl went up too; and as they went into the Queen’s bower, each
            held the other by the hand. <action actor="Queen" subject="adopted daughter"
                sign="negative">Then the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> began to scold the
                little lady, and to say:</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="adopted daughter">“You ought to be above running
                about and playing with a <descriptor subject="beggar wife's daughter"
                    sign="negative" speaker="Queen">tattered</descriptor> beggar’s brat.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>And so she wanted to drive the lassie downstairs.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="beggar wife's daughter" subject="Queen">“If the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> only knew my mother’s power, she’d not drive me out”, said
                the <character who="beggar wife's daughter">little lassie</character></dialogue>;
            and when the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> asked what she meant more plainly,
                <dialogue subject="Queen" speaker="beggar wife's daughter">she told her how her
                mother could get her children if she chose.</dialogue> The <character who="Queen"
                >Queen</character> wouldn’t believe it, but the <character
                who="beggar wife's daughter">lassie</character> held her own, and said every word of
            it was true, and bade the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> only to try and make
            her mother do it. <action actor="Queen" subject="beggar wife's daughter" sign="neutral"
                >So the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> sent the <character
                    who="beggar wife's daughter">lassie</character> down to fetch up her
                mother.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="old beggar wife">“Do you know what your daughter
                says?” asked the <character who="Queen">Queen</character></dialogue> of the old
            woman, as soon as ever she came into the room.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old beggar wife" subject="Queen">No</dialogue>; the beggar wife knew
            nothing about it.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="old beggar wife">“Well, she says you can get me
                children if you will”, answered the <character who="Queen"
                >Queen</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old beggar wife" subject="Queen">“Queens shouldn’t listen to beggar
                lassies’ silly stories”, said the old wife</dialogue>, and strode out of the
            room.</p>
        <p>Then the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> got angry, and wanted again to drive
            out the <character who="beggar wife's daughter">little lassie</character>; but she
            declared it was true every word that she had said.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="little girl" subject="Queen">“Let the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> only give my mother a drop to drink,” said the <character
                    who="beggar wife's daughter">lassie</character>; “when she gets merry she’ll
                soon find out a way to help you.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Queen" subject="old beggar wife" sign="positive">The <character
                    who="Queen">Queen</character> was ready to try this; so the <character
                    who="old beggar wife">beggar wife</character> was fetched up again once more,
                and treated both with wine and mead as much as she chose; and so it was not long
                before her tongue began to wag. Then the <character who="Queen">Queen</character>
                came out again with the same question she had asked before.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="old beggar wife" subject="Queen">“One way to help you perhaps I
                know”, said the beggar wife. “Your Majesty must make them bring in two pails of
                water some evening before you go to bed. In each of them you must wash yourself, and
                afterwards throw away the water under the bed. When you look under the bed next
                morning, <descriptor subject="flowers" sign="neutral" speaker="old beggar wife">two
                    flowers will have sprung up, one fair and one ugly.</descriptor> The fair one
                you must eat, the ugly one you must let stand; but mind you don’t forget the
                last.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>That was what the <character who="old beggar wife">beggar wife</character> said.</p>
        <p><action actor="Queen" subject="flowers" sign="neutral">Yes; the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> did what the beggar wife advised her to do; she had the water
                brought up in two pails, washed herself in them, and emptied them under the bed; and
                lo! when she looked under the bed next morning, there stood two flowers; <descriptor
                    subject="ugly flower" sign="negative" speaker="Queen">one was ugly and foul, and
                    had black leaves;</descriptor>
                <descriptor subject="pretty flower" sign="positive" speaker="Queen">but the other
                    was so bright, and fair, and lovely, she had never seen its like;</descriptor>
                so she ate it up at once. <action actor="Queen" subject="ugly flower"
                    sign="negative">But the pretty flower tasted so sweet, that she couldn’t help
                    herself. She ate the other up too,</action> for, she thought,</action>
            <dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="herself">“it can’t hurt or help one much either way,
                I’ll be bound”.</dialogue></p>
        <p>Well, sure enough, after a while the <character who="Queen">Queen</character> was brought
            to bed. <descriptor subject="Queen" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">First of all, she
                had a <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative"
                    >girl</descriptor> who had a wooden spoon in her hand, and rode upon a goat;
                loathly and ugly she was, and the very moment she came into the world</descriptor>,
            she bawled out <dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Queen">“Mamma”</dialogue>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="Tatterhood"><descriptor subject="Tatterhood"
                    sign="negative" speaker="Queen">“If I’m your mamma”, said the <character
                        who="Queen">Queen</character>, “God give me grace to mend my
                    ways.”</descriptor></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Queen">“Oh, don’t be sorry”, said the girl, who
                rode on the goat, “for one will soon come after me who is better
                looking.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So, after a while, <descriptor subject="Queen" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">the
                    <character who="Queen">Queen</character> had <character>another
                girl</character></descriptor>, <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="younger twin"
                sign="neutral">who was so fair and sweet, no one had ever set eyes on such a lovely
                child</descriptor>, and with her you may fancy the <character who="Queen"
                >Queen</character> was very well pleased. The <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="Tatterhood" sign="neutral"><descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="neutral"
                    speaker="narrator">elder twin</descriptor> they called “<character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>”, because she was always so ugly and
                ragged, and because she had a hood which hung about her ears in
            tatters</descriptor>. <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative" speaker="Queen"
                >The <character who="Queen">Queen</character> could scarce bear to look at her, and
                the nurses tried to shut her up in a room by herself, <descriptor
                    subject="younger twin and Tatterhood" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">but it
                    was all no good; where the younger twin was, there she must also be, and no one
                    could ever keep them apart.</descriptor></descriptor></p>
        <p><descriptor subject="Christmas eve" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">Well, one
                Christmas eve, <descriptor subject="Tatterhood and younger twin" sign="" speaker=""
                    >when they were half grown up</descriptor>, there rose such a frightful noise
                and clatter in the gallery outside the Queen’s bower.</descriptor>
            <dialogue subject="Queen" speaker="Tatterhood">So <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> asked what it was that dashed and crashed so out in the
                passage.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Queen" subject="Tatterhood">“Oh!” said the Queen, “it isn’t worth
                asking about.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>But <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> wouldn’t give over till she found
            out all about it and <dialogue subject="Tatterhood" speaker="Queen">so the <character
                    who="Queen">Queen</character> told her it was a pack of Trolls and witches who
                had come there to keep Christmas.</dialogue>
            <dialogue subject="Queen" speaker="Tatterhood">So <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> said she’d just go out and drive them away;</dialogue>
            and in spite of all they could say, and however much they begged and prayed her to let
            the Trolls alone, she must and would go out to drive the witches off; but <dialogue
                speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Queen">she begged the <character who="Queen"
                    >Queen</character> to mind and keep all the doors close shut, so that not one of
                them came so much as the least bit ajar.</dialogue> Having said this, <action
                actor="Tatterhood" subject="trolls and witches" sign="positive">off she went with
                her wooden spoon, and began to hunt and sweep away the hags</action>; <descriptor
                subject="palace" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">and all this while there was
                such a pother out in the gallery, the like of it was never heard. The whole Palace
                creaked and groaned as if every joint and beam were going to be torn out of its
                place. Now, how it was, I’m sure I can’t tell; but somehow or other one door did get
                the least bit ajar,</descriptor>
            <action actor="witch" subject="younger twin" sign="negative">then <character
                    who="younger twin">her twin sister</character> just peeped out to see how things
                were going with <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>, and put her head
                a tiny bit through the opening. But, POP! up came an old witch, and whipped off her
                head, and stuck a calf’s head on her shoulders instead; and <descriptor
                    subject="younger twin" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">so the <character
                        who="younger twin">Princess</character> ran back into the room on all-fours,
                    and began to “moo” like a calf.</descriptor></action> When <character
                who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> came back and saw her sister, she scolded
            them all round, and was very angry because they hadn’t kept better watch, and asked them
            what they thought of their heedlessness now, when her sister was turned into a calf.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="everyone">“But still I’ll see if I can’t set her
                free”, she said.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">Then she asked the King for a ship in full trim, and well fitted with stores; but captain
            and sailors she wouldn’t have. No; she would sail away with her sister all alone; and as
            there was no holding her back, at last they let her have her own way.</descriptor></p>
        <p><action actor="Tatterhood" subject="ship" sign="positive">Then <character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> sailed off, and steered her ship right
                under the land where the witches dwelt, and when she came to the landing-place, she
                told her sister to stay quite still on board the ship;</action>
            <action actor="Tatterhood" subject="witches" sign="positive">but she herself rode on her
                goat up to the witches’ castle. When she got there, one of the windows in the
                gallery was open, and there she saw her sister’s head hung up on the window frame;
                so she leapt her goat through the window into the gallery, snapped up the head, and
                set off with it. After her came the witches to try to get the head again, and they
                flocked about her as thick as a swarm of bees or a nest of ants; but the goat
                snorted, and puffed, and butted with his horns, and <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> beat and banged them about with her wooden spoon; and so
                the pack of witches had to give it up.</action>
            <action actor="Tatterhood" subject="younger twin" sign="positive">So <character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> got back to her ship, took the calf’s
                head off her sister, and put her own on again, and then she became a girl as she had
                been before.</action> After that she sailed a long, long way, to a strange king’s
            realm.</p>
        <p>Now the <character who="foreign king">king</character> of that land <descriptor
                subject="foreign king" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">was a widower, and had an
                only son.</descriptor>
            <action actor="foreign king" subject="foreign king's men" sign="neutral">So when he saw
                the strange sail, he sent <character who="foreign king's men">messengers</character>
                down to the strand to find out whence it came, and who owned it; but when the
                    <character who="foreign king's men">king’s men</character> came down there,
                    <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="positive" speaker="foreign king's men"
                    >they saw never a living soul on board but <character who="Tatterhood"
                        >Tatterhood</character>, and there she was, riding round and round the deck
                    on her goat at full speed, till her elf locks streamed again in the
                    wind.</descriptor></action> The folk from the palace were all amazed at this
            sight, <dialogue subject="Tatterhood" speaker="foreign king's men">and asked, were there
                not more on board?</dialogue>
            <dialogue subject="foreign king's men" speaker="Tatterhood">Yes, there were; she had a
                sister with her, said Tatterhood.</dialogue> Her, too, they wanted to see, <dialogue
                subject="foreign king's men" speaker="Tatterhood">but <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> said “No”:</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="foreign king's men">“No one shall see her, unless
                the king comes himself”, she said;</dialogue> and so <descriptor
                subject="Tatterhood" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">she began to gallop about on
                her goat till the deck thundered again.</descriptor></p>
        <p><action actor="foreign king's men" subject="foreign king" sign="neutral">So when the
                servants got back to the palace, and told what they had seen and heard down at the
                ship,</action>
            <action actor="foreign king" subject="ship" sign="neutral">the <character
                    who="foreign king">king</character> was for setting out at once, that he might
                see the lassie that rode on the goat. When he got down, <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> led out her sister, and she was so fair and gentle, the
                    <descriptor subject="younger twin" sign="positive" speaker="foreign king"
                        ><character who="foreign king">king</character> fell over head and ears in
                    love with her as he stood. He brought them both back with him to the Palace, and
                    wanted to have the sister for his queen;</descriptor></action> but <character
                who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> said <dialogue speaker="Tatterhood"
                subject="King">“No”; the <character who="foreign king">king</character> couldn’t
                have her in any way, unless the <character who="Prince">king’s son</character> chose
                to have <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>.</dialogue> That you may
            fancy the <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative" speaker="narrator"><character
                    who="Prince">prince</character> was very loath to do,</descriptor>
            <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">such an ugly hussy as
                    <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> was;</descriptor> but at last
            the <character who="foreign king">king</character> and all the others in the palace
            talked him over, and he yielded, giving his word to take her for his queen; but it went
            sore against the grain, and he was a doleful man.</p>
        <p>Now they set about the wedding, both with brewing and baking; and when all was ready,
            they were to go to church; but the <character who="Prince">prince</character> thought it
            the weariest churching he had ever had in all his life. <descriptor
                subject="foreign king and younger twin" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">First,
                the <character who="foreign king">king</character> drove off with his bride, and she
                was so lovely and so grand, all the people stopped to look after her all along the
                road, and they stared at her till she was out of sight.</descriptor>
            <descriptor subject="Tatterhood Prince" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">After them
                came the <character who="Prince">prince</character> on horseback by the side of
                    <character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>, who trotted along on her
                goat with her wooden spoon in her fist, and to look at him, it was more like going
                to a burial than a wedding, and that his own; so sorrowful he seemed, and with never
                a word to say.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Why don’t you talk?” asked <character
                    who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character>, when they had ridden a bit.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why, what should I talk about?”
                answered the <character who="Prince">prince</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Well, you might at least ask me why I
                ride upon this ugly goat”, said <character who="Tatterhood"
                >Tatterhood</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why do you ride on that <descriptor
                    subject="goat" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">ugly goat</descriptor>?” asked
                the <character who="Prince">prince</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Is it an ugly goat? why, it’s the
                grandest horse bride ever rode on”, answered <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character>;</dialogue>
            <misconception actor="Prince" subject="goat" sign="positive">and in a trice the goat
                became a horse, and that the finest the <character who="Prince">prince</character>
                had ever set eyes on.</misconception>
        </p>
        <p>Then they rode on again a bit, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">but the <character who="Prince">prince</character> was just as
                woeful as before, and couldn’t get a word out.</descriptor>
            <dialogue subject="Prince" speaker="Tatterhood">So <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character> asked him again why he didn’t talk,</dialogue> and when
                <dialogue subject="Tatterhood" speaker="Prince">the Prince answered he didn’t know
                what to talk about,</dialogue> she said:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“You can at least ask me why I ride with
                this ugly spoon in my fist.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why do you ride with that <descriptor
                    subject="wand" sign="negative" speaker="Prince"/>ugly spoon? “asked the
                    <character who="Prince">prince</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Is it an ugly spoon? why, it’s the
                loveliest silver wand bride ever bore”, said <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character>;</dialogue>
            <misconception actor="Prince" subject="wand" sign="positive"> and in a trice it became a
                silver wand, so dazzling bright, the sunbeams glistened from it.</misconception>
        </p>
        <p>So they rode on another bit, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">but the Prince was just as sorrowful, and said never a
                word.</descriptor> In a little while, <dialogue subject="Prince"
                speaker="Tatterhood"><character who="Tatterhood">Tatterhood</character> asked him
                again why he didn’t talk, and bade him ask why she wore that ugly grey hood on her
                head.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Why do you wear that <descriptor
                    subject="hood" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">ugly grey hood on your
                    head</descriptor>?” asked the Prince.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“Is it an ugly hood? why, it’s the
                brightest golden crown bride ever wore”, answered <character who="Tatterhood"
                    >Tatterhood</character>,</dialogue>
            <misconception actor="Prince" subject="hood" sign="positive"> and it became a crown on
                the spot.</misconception>
        </p>
        <p>Now, they rode on a long while again, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="negative"
                speaker="narrator">and the Prince was so woeful, that he sat without sound or speech
                just as before.</descriptor>
            <dialogue subject="Prince" speaker="Tatterhood">So his bride asked him again why he
                didn’t talk, and bade him ask now, why her face was so ugly and
                ashen-grey?</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Prince" subject="Tatterhood">“Ah!” asked the Prince, “why is
                    <descriptor subject="Tatterhood" sign="negative" speaker="Prince">your face so
                    ugly and ashen-grey</descriptor>?”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Tatterhood" subject="Prince">“I ugly”, said the bride; “you think my
                sister pretty, but I am ten times prettier”;</dialogue> and lo!<misconception
                actor="Prince" subject="Tatterhood" sign="positive"> when the Prince looked at her,
                she was so lovely, he thought there never was so lovely a woman in all the
                world.</misconception> After that, I shouldn’t wonder if the Prince found his
            tongue, <descriptor subject="Prince" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">and no longer
                rode along hanging down his head.</descriptor></p>
        <p>So they drank the bridal cup both deep and long, and, after that, both <character
                who="Prince">Prince</character> and King set out with their brides to the Princess’s
            father’s palace, and there they had another bridal feast, and drank anew, both deep and
            long. There was no end to the fun; and, if you make haste and run to the King’s palace,
            I dare say you’ll find there’s still a drop of the bridal ale left for you.</p>
    </body>
</story>
