<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="norseTalesSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story>
    <title>THE GIANT WHO HAD NO HEART IN HIS BODY</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time there was a <character who="King">king</character>
            <descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="King" sign="neutral">who had seven sons, and he
                loved them so much that he could never bear to be without them all at once, but one
                must always be with him.</descriptor> Now, when they were grown up, <character
                who="Princes">six</character> were to set off to woo, but as for the <descriptor
                speaker="Narrator" subject="Boots" sign="neutral">youngest</descriptor>, his father
            kept him at home, and the others were to bring back a princess for him to the palace.
                <action actor="King" subject="princes" sign="positive">So the king gave the six the
                finest clothes you ever set eyes on, so fine that the light gleamed from them a long
                way off, and each had his horse, which cost many, many hundred dollars, and so they
                set off.</action><descriptor subject="princes" sign="neutral" speaker="Narrator">
                Now, when they had been to many palaces, and seen many princesses, at last they came
                to a king who had <character who="princesses">six daughters</character>; such lovely
                king’s daughters they had never seen, and so they fell to wooing them, each one, and
                when they had got them for sweethearts, they set off home again</descriptor>,
                <action subject="Boots" sign="negative" actor="princes">but they quite forgot that
                they were to bring back with them a sweetheart for <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character>, their brother, who stayed at home, for they were over head
                and ears in love with their own sweethearts.</action></p>
        <p>But when they had gone a good bit on their way, they passed close by a steep hill-side,
            like a wall, where the giant’s house was, and there the <character who="Giant"
                >giant</character> came out, and set his eyes upon them, and <action actor="Giant"
                subject="princes and princesses" sign="negative">turned them all into stone, princes
                and princesses and all.</action>
            <descriptor subject="King" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">Now the king waited and
                waited for his six sons, but the more he waited, the longer they stayed away; so he
                fell into great trouble, and said he should never know what it was to be glad
                again.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="King" subject="Boots">“And if I had not you left”, he said to
                    <character who="Boots">Boots</character>, “I would live no longer, so full of
                sorrow am I for the loss of your brothers.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="King">“Well, but now I’ve been thinking to ask your
                leave to set out and find them again; that’s what I’m thinking of”, said <character
                    who="Boots">Boots</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="King" subject="Boots">“Nay, nay!” said his father; “that leave you
                shall never get, for then you would stay away too.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>But <character who="Boots">Boots</character> had set his heart upon it; go he would; and
            he begged and prayed so long that the <character who="King">king</character> was forced
            to let him go. <descriptor subject="King" sign="negative" speaker="narrator">Now, you
                must know the king had no other horse to give <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> but an old broken-down jade, for his six other sons and their
                train had carried off all his horses;</descriptor> but <character who="Boots"
                >Boots</character> did not care a pin for that, he sprang up on his
            sorry-old-steed.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="King">“Farewell, father”, said he; “I’ll come back,
                never fear, and like enough I shall bring my six brothers back with me”; and with
                that he rode off.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So, when he had ridden a while, he came to a <character who="Raven">Raven</character>,
                <descriptor subject="Raven" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">which lay in the road
                and flapped its wings, and was not able to get out of the way, it was so
                starved.</descriptor></p>
        <p><fig_lang type="personification" subject="Raven">“Oh, dear friend”, said the <character
                    who="Raven">Raven</character>, “give me a little food, and I’ll help you again
                at your utmost need.”</fig_lang>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Raven">“I haven’t much food”, said the <character
                    who="Boots">Prince</character>, “and I don’t see how you’ll ever be able to help
                me much; but still I can spare you a little. I see you want it.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Boots" subject="Raven" sign="positive">So he gave the <character
                    who="Raven">raven</character> some of the food he had brought with him.</action>
        </p>
        <p>Now, when he had gone a bit further, he came to a brook, and in the brook lay a
                <character who="Salmon">great Salmon</character>, <descriptor subject="Salmon"
                sign="neutral" speaker="narrator">which had got upon a dry place and dashed itself
                about, and could not get into the water again.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Salmon" subject="Boots"><fig_lang type="personification"
                    subject="Salmon">“Oh, dear friend”, said the <character who="Salmon"
                        >Salmon</character> to the <character who="Boots">Prince</character>; “shove
                    me out into the water again, and I’ll help you again at your utmost
                    need.”</fig_lang></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Salmon">“Well!” said the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character>, “the help you’ll give me will not be great, I daresay, but
                it’s a pity you should lie there and choke”</dialogue>; and with that <action
                actor="Boots" subject="Salmon" sign="positive">he shot the fish out into the stream
                again.</action></p>
        <p>After that he went a long, long way, and there met him a <character who="Wolf"
                >Wolf</character>, which was so famished that it lay and crawled along the road on
            its belly.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots"><fig_lang type="personification" subject="Wolf"
                    >“Dear friend, do let me have your horse”, said the <character who="Wolf"
                        >Wolf</character>; “I’m so hungry the wind whistles through my ribs; I’ve
                    had nothing to eat these two years.”</fig_lang></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Wolf">“No”, said <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character>, “this will never do; “first I came to a <character
                    who="Raven">raven</character>, and I was forced to give him my food; next I came
                to a <character who="Salmon">salmon</character>, and him I had to help into the
                water again; and now you will have my horse. It can’t be done, that it can’t, for
                then I should have nothing to ride on.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Nay, dear friend, but you can help me”, said
                    <character who="Wolf">Graylegs the wolf</character>; “you can ride upon my back,
                and I’ll help you again in your utmost need.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Well! the help I shall get from you will not
                be great, I’ll be bound”, said the <character who="Boots">Prince</character>; “but
                you may take my horse, since you are in such need.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Wolf" subject="Boots" sign="postive">So when the <character who="Wolf"
                    >wolf</character> had eaten the horse, <character who="Boots">Boots</character>
                took the bit and put it into the wolf’s jaw, and laid the saddle on his back;
                    <descriptor subject="Wolf" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">and now the
                        <character who="Wolf">wolf</character> was so strong, after what he had got
                    inside, that he set off with the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> like
                    nothing. So fast he had never ridden before.</descriptor></action>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“When we have gone a bit farther”, <character
                    who="Wolf">said Graylegs</character>; “I’ll show you the Giant’s
                house.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So after a while they came to it.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots"><descriptor subject="Giant's House"
                    sign="negative" speaker="Wolf">“See, here is the Giant’s house”, said the
                        <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>; “and see, here are your six
                    brothers, whom the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> has turned into
                    stone; and see here are their six brides, and away yonder is the door, and in at
                    that door you must go.”</descriptor></dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Wolf">“Nay, but I daren’t go in”, said the <character
                    who="Boots">Prince</character>; “he’ll take my life.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“No! no!” said the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character>; “when you get in you’ll find a Princess, and she’ll tell you
                what to do to make an end of the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>. Only mind
                and do as she bids you.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Well! <character who="Boots">Boots</character> went in, but, truth to say, he was very
            much afraid. When he came in the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> was away, but
            in one of the rooms sat the <character who="Princess">Princess</character>, just as the
                <character who="Wolf">wolf</character> had said, <descriptor speaker="Boots"
                subject="Princess" sign="positive">and so lovely a princess <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> had never yet set eyes on.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Oh! heaven help you! whence have you
                come?” said the <character who="Princess">Princess</character>, as she saw him; “it
                will surely be your death. No one can make an end of the Giant who lives here, for
                he has no heart in his body.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“Well! well!” said <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character>; “but now that I am here, I may as well try what I can do
                with him; and I will see if I can’t free my brothers, who are standing turned to
                stone out of doors; and you, too, I will try to save, that I will.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Well, if you must, you must”, said the
                    <character who="Princess">Princess</character>; “and so let us see if we can’t
                hit on a plan. Just creep under the bed yonder, and mind and listen to what he and I
                talk about. But, pray, do lie as still as a mouse.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Boots" subject="bed" sign="neutral">So he crept under the bed, and he had
                scarce got well underneath it,</action> before the <character who="Giant"
                >Giant</character> came.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Ha!” roared the <character who="Giant"
                    >Giant</character>, “what a smell of Christian blood there is in the
                house!”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Yes, I know there is”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>, “for there came a magpie flying with a
                man’s bone, and let it fall down the chimney. I made all the haste I could to get it
                out, but all one can do, the smell doesn’t go off so soon.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> said no more about it, and when night
            came, they went to bed. After they had lain awhile, the <character who="Princess"
                >Princess</character> said:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“There is one thing I’d be so glad to ask
                you about, if I only dared.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“What thing is that?” asked the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Only where it is you keep your heart,
                since you don’t carry it about you”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Ah! that’s a thing you’ve no business to
                ask about; but if you must know, it lies under the door-sill”, said the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Boots">“Ho! ho!” said <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> to himself under the bed, “then we’ll soon see if we can’t
                find it.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Next morning the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> got up cruelly early, and
            strode off to the wood; but he was hardly out of the house before <action
                actor="Boots and Princess" subject="Giant's heart" sign="neutral"><character
                    who="Boots">Boots</character> and the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character> set to work to look under the door-sill for his heart; but
                the more they dug, and the more they hunted, the more they couldn’t find
                it.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“He has baulked us this time”, said the
                    <character who="Princess">Princess</character>, “but we’ll try him once
                more.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Princess" subject="flowers" sign="positive">So she picked all the
                prettiest flowers she could find, and strewed them over the door-sill, which they
                had laid in its right place again</action>; and when the time came for the
                <character who="Giant">Giant</character> to come home again,<action actor="Boots"
                subject="bed" sign="neutral">
                <character who="Boots">Boots</character> crept under the bed.</action> Just as he
            was well under, back came the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</p>
        <p>Snuff—snuff, went the Giant’s nose. <dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“My eyes
                and limbs, what a smell of Christian blood there is in here”, said
            he.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“I know there is”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>, “for there came a magpie flying with a
                man’s bone in his bill, and let it fall down the chimney. I made as much haste as I
                could to get it out, but I daresay it’s that you smell.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> held his peace, and said no more about
            it. A little while after, he asked who it was that had strewed flowers about the
            door-sill.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Oh, I, of course”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“And, pray, what’s the meaning of all
                this?” said the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Ah!” said the Princess, “I’m so fond of
                you that I couldn’t help strewing them, when I knew that your heart lay under
                there.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“You don’t say so”, said the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>; “but after all it doesn’t lie there at
                all.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>So when they went to bed again in the evening, the <character who="Princess"
                >Princess</character> asked the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> again where
            his heart was, for she said she would so like to know.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Well”, said the <character who="Giant"
                    >Giant</character>, “if you must know, it lies away yonder in the cupboard
                against the wall.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots and Princess" subject="themselves">“So, so!” thought <character
                    who="Boots">Boots</character> and the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>; “then we’ll soon try to find it.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Next morning the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> was away early, and strode off
            to the wood, and so soon as he was gone <action actor="Boots and Princess"
                subject="Giant's heart" sign="neutral"><character who="Boots">Boots</character> and
                the <character who="Princess">Princess</character> were in the cupboard hunting for
                his heart, but the more they sought for it, the less they found it.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Well”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>, “we’ll just try him once more.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Princess" subject="decorating cupboard" sign="positive">So she decked out
                the cupboard with flowers and garlands, and when the time came for the Giant to come
                home, <action actor="Boots" subject="bed" sign="neutral"><character who="Boots"
                        >Boots</character> crept under the bed again.</action></action>
        </p>
        <p>Then back came the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</p>
        <p>Snuff-snuff! <dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“My eyes and limbs, what a
                smell of Christian blood there is in here!”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“I know there is”, said the <character
                    who="Princess">Princess</character>; “for a little while since there came a
                magpie flying with a man’s bone in his bill, and let it fall down the chimney. I
                made all the haste I could to get it out of the house again; but after all my pains,
                I daresay it’s that you smell.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>When the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> heard that, he said no more about it;
            but a little while after, he saw how the cupboard was all decked about with flowers and
            garlands; so he asked who it was that had done that? Who could it be but the <character
                who="Princess">Princess</character>.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“And, pray, what’s the meaning of all this
                tom-foolery?” asked the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Oh, I’m so fond of you, I couldn’t help
                doing it when I knew that your heart lay there”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“How can you be so silly as to believe any
                such thing?” said the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Oh yes; how can I help believing it, when
                you say it”, said the <character who="Princess">Princess</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“You’re a goose”, said the <character
                    who="Giant">Giant</character>; “where my heart is, you will never
                come.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Giant">“Well”, said the <character who="Princess"
                    >Princess</character>;” but for all that, ’twould be such a pleasure to know
                where it really lies.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>Then the poor <character who="Giant">Giant</character> could hold out no longer, but was
            forced to say:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Giant" subject="Princess">“Far, far away in a lake lies an island; on
                that island stands a church; in that church is a well; in that well swims a duck; in
                that duck there is an egg, and in that egg there lies my heart,—you
                darling!”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>In the morning early, while it was still grey dawn, the <character who="Giant"
                >Giant</character> strode off to the wood.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Yes! now I must set off too”, said
                    <character who="Boots">Boots</character>; “if I only knew how to find the
                way.”</dialogue> He took a long, long farewell of the <character who="Princess"
                >Princess</character>, <action actor="Wolf" subject="Boots" sign="positive">and when
                he got out of the Giant’s door, there stood the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character> waiting for him. So <character who="Boots">Boots</character>
                told him all that had happened inside the house, and said now he wished to ride to
                the well in the church, if he only knew the way. So the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character> bade him jump on his back, he’d soon find the way; and away
                they went, till the wind whistled after them, over hedge and field, over hill and
                dale. After they had travelled many, many days, they came at last to the lake. Then
                the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> did not know how to get over it, but
                the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character> bade him only not be afraid, but stick
                on, and so he jumped into the lake with the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> on his back, and swam over to the island. So they came to
                the church</action>; <descriptor subject="key" sign="negative" speaker="Boots"/>but
            the church keys hung high, high up on the top of the tower, and at first the <character
                who="Boots">Prince</character> did not know how to get them down.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“You must call on the <character who="Raven"
                    >raven</character>”, said the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p><action actor="Raven" subject="Boots" sign="positive">So the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> called on the <character who="Raven">raven</character>, and
                in a trice the <character who="Raven">raven</character> came, and flew up and
                fetched the keys, and so the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> got into the
                church</action>. But when he came to the well, there lay the duck, and swam about
            backwards and forwards, just as the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> had said.
                <action actor="Boots" subject="egg" sign="negative">So the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> stood and coaxed it and coaxed it, till it came to him, and
                he grasped it in his hand; but just as he lifted it up from the water the duck
                dropped the egg into the well, and then <character who="Boots">Boots</character> was
                beside himself to know how to get it out again.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Well, now you must call on the <character
                    who="Salmon">salmon</character> to be sure”, said the <character who="Wolf"
                    >Wolf</character></dialogue>; and the <character who="Boots">king’s
                son</character> called on the <character who="Salmon">salmon</character>, <action
                actor="Salmon" subject="Boots" sign="positive">and the <character who="Salmon"
                    >salmon</character> came and fetched up the egg from the bottom of the
                well.</action></p>
        <p>Then the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character> told him to <action actor="Boots"
                subject="Giant" sign="positive">squeeze the egg, and as soon as ever he squeezed it
                the <character who="Giant">Giant</character> screamed out.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Squeeze it again”, said the <character
                    who="Wolf">Wolf</character></dialogue>; <action actor="Boots" subject="Giant"
                sign="positive">and when the <character who="Boots">Prince</character> did so, the
                    <character who="Giant">Giant</character> screamed still more piteously,</action>
            and <descriptor speaker="Giant" subject="Boots" sign="neutral">begged and prayed so
                prettily to be spared, saying he would do all that the <character who="Boots"
                    >Prince</character> wished if he would only not squeeze his heart in
                two.</descriptor></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Tell him, if he will restore to life again your
                six brothers and their brides, whom he has turned to stone, you will spare his
                life”, said the <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue> Yes, the
                <character who="Giant">Giant</character> was ready to do that, and <action
                actor="Giant" subject="princes and princesses" sign="positive">he turned the six
                brothers into king’s sons again, and their brides into king’s
            daughters.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Wolf" subject="Boots">“Now, squeeze the egg in two”, said the
                    <character who="Wolf">Wolf</character>.</dialogue>
            <action actor="Boots" subject="Giant" sign="positive"> So <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> squeezed the egg to pieces, <descriptor subject="Giant"
                    sign="positive" speaker="narrator">and the <character who="Giant"
                        >Giant</character> burst at once.</descriptor></action>
        </p>
        <p>Now, when he had made an end of the <character who="Giant">Giant</character>, <descriptor
                subject="Boots, Princess, princes, and princess" sign="neutral" speaker="narrator"
                    ><character who="Boots">Boots</character> rode back again on the <character
                    who="Wolf">wolf</character> to the Giant’s house, and there stood all his six
                brothers alive and merry, with their brides. Then <character who="Boots"
                    >Boots</character> went into the hill-side after his bride, and so they all set
                off home again to their father’s house.</descriptor>
            <descriptor subject="King" sign="positive" speaker="narrator">And you may fancy how glad
                the old king was when he saw all his seven sons come back, each with his
                bride—</descriptor><dialogue speaker="King" subject="everyone"><descriptor
                    subject="Princess" sign="positive" speaker="King">“But the loveliest bride of
                    all is the <character who="Princess">bride of Boots</character>, after all”,
                    said the <character who="King">king</character>,</descriptor><descriptor
                    subject="Boots" sign="positive" speaker="King"> “and he shall sit uppermost at
                    the table, with her by his side.”</descriptor></dialogue></p>
        <p><action actor="King" subject="wedding" sign="positive"/>So he sent out, and called a
            great wedding-feast, and the mirth was both loud and long, and if they have not done
            feasting, why, they are still at it.</p>
    </body>
</story>
