<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="norseTalesSchema.rnc" type-"application/relax-ng-compact=syntax"?>

<story>
    <title>WHY THE SEA IS SALT</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time, but it was a long, long time ago, there were two brothers, one
                <descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="Rich Brother" sign="Positive"
                >rich</descriptor> and one <descriptor speaker="Narrartor" subject="Poor Brother"
                sign="Negative">poor</descriptor>. Now, one Christmas eve, the poor one hadn’t so
            much as a crumb in the house, either of meat or bread, so he went to his brother to ask
            him for something to keep Christmas with, in God’s name. It was not the first time his
            brother had been forced to help him, and you may fancy he wasn’t very glad to see his
            face, but he said:</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother">“If you will do what I ask you to
                do, I’ll give you a whole flitch of bacon.”</dialogue> So the <character
                who="Poor Brother">poor brother</character> said he would do anything, and was full
            of thanks.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother">“Well, here is the
                flitch”</dialogue>, said the <character who="Rich Brother">rich brother</character>,
            “and now go straight to Hell.”</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Rich Brother" speaker="Poor Brother">“What I have given my word to do,
                I must stick to”</dialogue>, said the other; so he took the flitch and set off. He
            walked the whole day, and at dusk he came to a place where he saw a very bright
            light.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Self" speaker="Poor Brother">“Maybe this is the place”</dialogue>,
            said the man to himself. So he turned aside, and the first thing he saw was an old,
                <character who="Old Man">old man</character>, with a long white beard, who stood in
            an outhouse, hewing wood for the Christmas fire. </p>
        <p>
            <dialogue subject="Old Man" speaker="Poor Brother">“Good even”</dialogue>, said the man
            with the flitch.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Old Man">“The same to you; whither are you
                going so late?”</dialogue> said the man.</p>
        <p>
            <dialogue subject="Old Man" speaker="Poor Brother">“Oh! I’m going to Hell, if I only
                knew the right way”</dialogue>, answered the poor man.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Old Man">“Well, you’re not far wrong, for this
                is Hell”</dialogue>, said the old man; <dialogue subject="Poor Brother"
                speaker="Old Man">“when you get inside they will be all for buying your flitch, for
                meat is scarce in Hell; but mind, you don’t sell it unless you get the hand-quern
                which stands behind the door for it. When you come out, I’ll <action actor="Old Man"
                    subject="Poor Brother" sign="Neutral"> teach</action> you how to handle the
                quern, for it’s good to grind almost anything.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So the man with the flitch <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Old Man" sign="Positive"
                >thanked</action> the other for his good advice, and gave a great knock at the
                <character who="Devil">Devil</character>’s door.</p>
        <p> When he got in, everything went just as the old man had said. All the devils, great and
            small, came swarming up to him like ants round an anthill, and each tried to outbid the
            other for the flitch. </p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Devil" speaker="Poor Brother">“Well!”</dialogue> said the man,
                <dialogue subject="Devil" speaker="Poor Brother"> "by rights my old dame and I ought
                to have this flitch for our Christmas dinner; but since you have all set your hearts
                on it, I suppose I must give it up to you; but if I sell it at all, I’ll have for it
                that quern behind the door yonder.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>At first the <character who="Devil">Devil</character> wouldn’t hear of such a bargain,
            and <action actor="Devil" subject="Poor Brother" sign="Neutral">chaffered and
                haggled</action> with the man; but he stuck to what he said, and at last the
                <character who="Devil">Devil</character> had to part with his quern. When the man
            got out into the yard, he asked the old woodcutter how he was to handle the quern; and
            after he had learned how to use it, he <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Old Man"
                sign="Positive">thanked</action> the old man and went off home as fast as he could,
            but still the clock had struck twelve on Christmas eve before he reached his own
            door.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Poor Brother's Wife">“Wherever in the world
                have you been?”</dialogue> said his <character who="Poor Brother's Wife">old
                dame</character>, <dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Poor Brother's Wife"
                >“here have I sat hour after hour <action actor="Poor Brother's Wife"
                    subject="Poor Brother" sign="Positive">waiting</action> and watching, without so
                much as two sticks to lay together under the Christmas brose.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>
            <dialogue subject="Poor Brother's Wife" speaker="Poor Brother">“Oh!”</dialogue> said the
            man, <dialogue subject="Poor Brother's Wife" speaker="Poor Brother">“I couldn’t get back
                before, for I had to go a long way first for one thing, and then for another; but
                now you shall see what you shall see.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So he put the quern on the table, and bade it first of all grind lights, then a
            table-cloth, then meat, then ale, and so on till they had got everything that was nice
            for Christmas fare. He had only to speak the word, and the quern ground out what he
            wanted. The old dame stood by blessing her stars, and kept on asking where he had got
            this wonderful quern, but he wouldn’t tell her.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother's Wife" speaker="Poor Brother">“It’s all one where I got
                it from; you see the quern is a good one, and the mill-stream never freezes, that’s
                enough.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So he ground meat and drink and dainties enough to last out till Twelfth Day, and on the
            third day he asked all his friends and kin to his house, and gave a great feast. Now,
            when his <character who="Rich Brother">rich brother</character> saw all that was on the
            table, and all that was behind in the larder, he grew quite <descriptor
                subject="Rich Brother" speaker="Narrator" sign="Negative">spiteful and
                wild</descriptor>, for he <action actor="Rich Brother" subject="Poor Brother"
                sign="Negative">couldn’t bear that his brother should have anything.</action></p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Party" speaker="Rich Brother">“’Twas only on Christmas
            eve”</dialogue>, he said to the rest, <dialogue subject="Party" speaker="Rich Brother"
                >“he was <descriptor subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother" sign="Negative"
                    >in such straits</descriptor>, that he came and asked for a morsel of food in
                God’s name, and now he gives a feast <descriptor speaker="Rich Brother"
                    subject="Poor Brother" sign="Negative">as if he were count or
                king</descriptor>”</dialogue>; and he turned to his brother and said:</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Poor Brother" speaker="Rich Brother">“But whence, in Hell’s name, have
                you got all this wealth?”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Rich Brother" speaker="Poor Brother">“From behind the
            door”</dialogue>, answered the <character who="Poor Brother">owner of the
                quern</character>, for he didn’t care to <fig_lang type="Metaphor" subject="Quern"
                relation="Revealing Secret" sign="Negative">let the cat out of the bag</fig_lang>.
            But later on the evening, when he had got a drop too much, he could keep his secret no
            longer, and brought out the quern and said:</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Party" speaker="Poor Brother">“There, you see what has gotten me all
                this wealth”</dialogue>; and so he made the quern grind all kind of things. When his
                <character who="Rich Brother">brother</character> saw it, he set his heart on having
            the quern, and, after a deal of <action actor="Rich Brother" subject="Poor Brother"
                sign="Neutral">coaxing</action>, he got it; but he had to pay three hundred dollars
            for it, and <character who="Poor Brother">his brother</character> bargained to keep it
            till hay-harvest, for he thought, if I keep it till then, I can make it grind meat and
            drink that will last for years. So you may fancy the quern didn’t grow rusty for want of
            work, and when hay-harvest came, the <character who="Rich Brother">rich
                brother</character> got it, but <character who="Poor Brother">the other</character>
            took care <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Rich Brother" sign="Negative">not to
                teach</action> him how to handle it. </p>
        <p>It was evening when the <character who="Rich Brother">rich brother</character> got the
            quern home, and next morning he told his wife to go out into the hay-field and toss,
            while the mowers cut the grass, and he would stay at home and get the dinner ready. So,
            when dinner-time drew near, he put the quern on the kitchen table and said:</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Self" speaker="Rich Brother">“Grind herrings and broth, and grind them
                good and fast.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>So the quern began to grind herrings and broth; first of all, all the dishes full, then
            all the tubs full, and so on till the kitchen floor was quite covered. Then the man
                <action subject="Quern" actor="Rich Brother" sign="Negative">twisted and
                twirled</action> at the quern to get it to stop, but for all his twisting and
            fingering the quern went on grinding, and in a little while the broth rose so high that
                <character who="Rich Brother">the man</character> was like to drown. So he threw
            open the kitchen door and ran into the parlour, but it wasn’t long before the quern had
            ground the parlour full too, and it was only at the risk of his life that the man could
            get hold of the latch of the house door through the stream of broth. When he got the
            door open, he ran out and set off down the road, with the stream of herrings and broth
            at his heels, roaring like a waterfall over the whole farm. Now, <character
                who="Rich Brother's Wife">his old dame</character>, who was in the field tossing
            hay, thought it a long time to dinner, and at last she said:</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Fieldworkers" speaker="Rich Brother's Wife">“Well! though <character
                    who="Rich Brother">the master</character> doesn’t call us home, we may as well
                go. Maybe he finds it hard work to boil the broth, and will be glad of my
                help.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>The men were willing enough, so they sauntered homewards; but just as they had got a
            little way up the hill, what should they meet but herrings, and broth, and bread, all
            running and dashing, and splashing together in a stream, and the master himself <action
                actor="Rich Brother" subject="Self" sign="Negative">running before them for his
                life</action>, and as he passed them he bawled out:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rich Brother" subject="Fieldworkers">“Would to heaven each of you had
                a hundred throats! but take care you’re not drowned in the broth.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Away he went, as though the <character who="Devil">Evil One</character> were at his
            heels, to <character who="Poor Brother">his brother</character>’s house, and begged him
            for God’s sake to take back the quern that instant; for, said he:</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Rich Brother" subject="Poor Brother">“If it grinds only one hour more,
                the whole parish will be swallowed up by herrings and broth.”</dialogue>
        </p>
        <p>But <character who="Poor Brother">his brother</character>
            <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Rich Brother" sign="Negative">wouldn’t hear of
                taking it back</action> till the other paid him down three hundred dollars more.</p>
        <p>So the<character who="Poor Brother">poor brother</character> got both the money and the
            quern, and it wasn’t long before he <action actor="Poor Brother" subject="Rich Brother"
                sign="Negative">set up a farm-house far finer than the one in which his brother
                lived</action>, and with the quern he ground so much gold that he covered it with
            plates of gold; and as the farm lay by the sea-side, the golden house gleamed and
            glistened far away over the sea. <transformation subject="Poor Brother" form="Rich Man">All who sailed by put ashore to see the <character
                who="Poor Brother">rich man</character> in the golden house</transformation>, and to see the
            wonderful quern, the fame of which spread far and wide, till there was nobody who hadn’t
            heard tell of it.</p>
        <p>So one day there came a <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> who wanted to see
            the quern; and the first thing he <action subject="Poor Brother" actor="Skipper"
                sign="Neutral">asked</action> was if it could grind salt.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Skipper" speaker="Poor Brother">“Grind salt!”</dialogue> said
                <character who="Poor Brother">the owner</character>; <dialogue subject="Skipper"
                speaker="Poor Brother">“I should just think it could. It can grind
                anything.”</dialogue> When the <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> heard
            that, he said he must have the quern, cost what it would; for if he only had it, he
            thought he should be rid of his long voyages across stormy seas for a lading of salt.
            Well, at first <character who="Poor Brother">the man</character> wouldn’t hear of
            parting with the quern; but the <character who="Skipper">skipper</character>
            <action actor="Skipper" subject="Poor Brother" sign="Neutral">begged and prayed</action>
            so hard, that at last he let him have it, but he had to pay many, many thousand dollars
            for it. Now, when the <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> had got the quern on
            his back, he soon made off with it, for he was <action actor="Skipper"
                subject="Poor Brother" sign="Negative">afraid lest the man should change his
                mind</action>; so he had no time to ask how to handle the quern, but got on board
            his ship as fast as he could, and set sail. When he had sailed a good way off, he
            brought the quern on deck and said:</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Self" speaker="Skipper">“Grind salt, and grind both good and
                fast.”</dialogue></p>
        <p>Well, the quern began to grind salt so that it poured out like water; and when the
                <character who="Skipper">skipper</character> had got the ship full, he wished to
            stop the quern, but whichever way he turned it, and however much he tried, it was no
            good; the quern kept grinding on, and the heap of salt grew higher and higher, and at
            last down sank the ship. </p>
        <p>There lies the quern at the bottom of the sea, and grinds away at this very day, and
            that’s why the sea is salt.</p>
    </body>
</story>
