
<?xml-model href="../../Norse-Tales/norseTalesSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<story><title>BOOTS WHO ATE A MATCH WITH THE TROLL</title>
<body><p><descriptor speaker="Narrator" subject="Father" sign="neutral">Once on a time there was a <character>farmer</character> who had <character>three sons</character>; his means were small, and he was old and weak, and his <character>sons</character> <action actor="Sons" subject="self" sign="negative">would take to nothing.</action></descriptor> A fine large wood belonged to the farm, and one day the <action actor="Father" subject="sons" sign="neutral"><character>father</character> told his <character who="Eldest,Middle, and Boots">sons</character> to go and hew wood, and try to pay off some of his debts.</action></p>
<p>Well, <action actor="Father" subject="sons" sign="positive">after a long talk he got them to set off</action>, and <character>the eldest</character> was to go first. But when he had <action actor="eldest Son" subject="Troll" sign="neutral">got well into the wood, and began to hew at a mossy old fir, what should he see coming up to him but a great sturdy <character>Troll</character>.</action></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="troll" subject="eldest son">“If you hew in this wood of mine”, said the <character>Troll</character>, “I’ll kill you!”</dialogue></p>
<p>When the <character who="Eldest">lad</character> <action actor="eldest son" subject="self" sign="">heard that, he threw the axe down, and ran off home as fast as he could lay legs to the ground</action>; so he came in quite out of breath, and told them what had happened, but his <character>father</character> <action actor="father" subject="eldest son" sign="negative">called him “hare-heart”</action>—no <character>Troll</character> would ever have scared him from hewing when he was young, he said.</p>
<p>Next day the <character who="Middle">second son's</character> turn came, and he fared just the same. <action actor="Middle" subject="Troll" sign="neutral">He had scarce hewn three strokes at the fir, before the <character>Troll</character> came to him too</action>, and said:</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="troll" subject="second son">“If you hew in this wood of mine, I’ll kill you.”</dialogue></p>
<p>The <character who="Middle">lad</character> dared not so much as look at him, but <action actor="Middle" subject="self" sign="negative">threw down the axe, took to his heels, and came scampering home just like his <character>brother</character>.</action> So when he got home, his <character>father</character> was angry again, and said no <character>Troll</character> had ever scared him when he was young.</p>
<p>The third day <character>Boots</character> wanted to set off.</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="older sons" subject="boots"><misconception actor="Elder Brothers" subject="Boots" sign="negative">“You, indeed!” said the <character>two elder brothers</character>; “you’ll do it bravely, no doubt! you, who have scarce ever set your foot out of the door.</misconception>”</dialogue></p>
<p><character>Boots</character> said nothing to this, but only <action actor="Boots" subject="Family" sign="neutral">begged them to give him a good store of food</action>. His <character>mother</character> had no cheese, so <action actor="Mother" subject="Boots" sign="postivie">she set the pot on the fire to make him a little, and he put it into a scrip and set off.</action> So when he had hewn a bit, the <character>Troll</character> came to him too, and said:</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="troll" subject="Boots">“If you hew in this wood of mine, I’ll kill you.”</dialogue></p>
<p>But the <character who="Boots">lad</character> was not slow; <action actor="Boots" subject="Troll" sign="Positive">he pulled his cheese out of the scrip in a trice, and squeezed it till the whey spurted out.</action></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Troll">“Hold your tongue!” he cried to the <character>Troll</character>, “or I’ll squeeze you as I squeeze the water out of this white stone.”</dialogue></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Troll" subject="Boots">“Nay, dear friend!” said the <character>Troll</character>, <misconception actor="Troll" subject="Boots" sign="Positive">“only spare me, and I’ll help you to hew.”</misconception></dialogue></p>
<p>Well, on those terms the <character who="Boots">lad</character> was willing to spare him, and the <character>Troll</character> <action actor="Boots and Troll" subject="self" sign="positive">hewed so bravely, that they felled and cut up many, many fathoms in the day.</action></p>
<p>But when even drew near, the <character>Troll</character> said:</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Troll" subject="Boots">“Now you’d better come home with me, for my house is nearer than yours.”</dialogue></p>
<p>So the <character who="Boots">lad</character> was willing enough; and when they reached the <character>Troll</character>’s house, <action actor="Troll and Boots" subject="self" sign="positive">the <character>Troll</character> was to make up the fire, while the lad went to fetch water for their porridge, and there stood two iron pails so big and heavy, that he couldn’t so much as lift them from the ground</action>.</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="self">“Pooh!” said the <character>lad</character>, “it isn’t worth while to touch these finer-basins: I’ll just go and fetch the spring itself.”</dialogue></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Troll" subject="Boots">“Nay, nay, dear friend!” said the <character>Troll</character>; <misconception actor="Troll" subject="Boots" sign="positive">“I can’t afford to lose my spring; just you make up the fire, and I’ll go and fetch the water.</misconception>”</dialogue></p>
<p>So<action actor="Troll and Boots" subject="self" sign="positive"> when he came back with the water, they set to and boiled up a great pot of porridge</action>.</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Troll">“It’s all the same to me”, said the <character who="Boots">lad</character>; “but if you’re of my mind, we’ll eat a match!”</dialogue></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Troll" subject="Boots">“With all my heart”, said the <character>Troll</character>, for he thought he could surely hold his own in eating. So they sat down; but the <character who="Boots">lad</character><action actor="Boots" subject="self" sign="neutral"> took his scrip unawares to the <character>Troll</character>, and hung it before him, and so he spooned more into the scrip than he ate himself; and when the scrip was full, he took up his knife and made a slit in the scrip.</action> <action actor="Troll" subject="self" sign="neutral">The <character>Troll</character> looked on all the while, but said never a word. So when they had eaten a good bit longer, the <character>Troll</character> laid down his spoon, saying, “Nay! but I can’t eat a morsel more.”</action></dialogue></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Troll">“But you shall eat”, said the <character who="Boots">youth</character>; “I’m only half done; why don’t you do as I did, and cut a hole in your paunch? You’ll be able to eat then as much as you please.”</dialogue></p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Troll" subject="self">“But doesn’t it hurt one cruelly?”</dialogue> asked the <character>Troll</character>.</p>
<p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Troll">“Oh”, said the <character>youth</character>, “nothing to speak of.”</dialogue></p>
<p>So <action actor="Troll" subject="self" sign="negative">the <character>Troll</character> did as the <character>lad</character> said, and then you must know very well that he lost his life</action>; but the <character who="Boots">lad</character> <action actor="Boots" subject="self and family" sign="positive">took all the silver and gold that he found in the hill-side, and went home with it, and you may fancy it went a great way to pay off the debt</action>.</p>
</body></story>