<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="norseTalesSchema.rnc" type-"application/relax-ng-compact=syntax"?>

<story>
    <title>TAMING THE SHREW</title>
    <body>
        <p>Once on a time there was a <character>king</character>, and he had a
                <character>daughter</character> who was such <descriptor speaker="narrator"
                subject="Princess" sign="negative">a scold</descriptor>, and whose<fig_lang
                type="personification" subject="Princess" sign="negative"> tongue went so fast,
                there was no stopping it</fig_lang>. So he gave out that the man who could stop her
            tongue should have the Princess to wife, and half his kingdom into the bargain. Now,
            three brothers, who heard this, made up their minds to go and try their luck; and first
            of all the two elder went, for they thought they were the cleverest; but they couldn’t
            cope with her at all, and got well thrashed besides.</p>
        <p> Then <character>Boots</character>, the <descriptor speaker="narrator" subject="Boots" sign="neutral">
            youngest</descriptor>, set off, and when he had gone a little way he found an ozier
            band lying on the road, and he picked it up. When he had gone a little farther he found
            a piece of a broken plate, and he picked that up too. A little farther on he found a
            dead magpie, and a little farther on still, a crooked ram’s horn; so he went on a bit
            and found the fellow to the horn; and at last, just as he was crossing the fields by the
            king’s palace, where they were pitching out dung, he found a worn-out shoe-sole. All
            these things he took with him into the palace, and went before the Princess.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots"> “Good day”</dialogue>, said he.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">
            “Good day”</dialogue>, said she, and made a wry face.</p> 
        <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Can I get my magpie cooked here?”</dialogue> he asked.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“I’m afraid it will burst”</dialogue>,answered the Princess.</p>
        <p> <dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Oh! never fear! for I’ll just tie this ozier band round it”</dialogue>,
            said the lad, as he pulled it out.</p>
        <p> <dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“The fat will run out of it”</dialogue>, said the Princess.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Princess" speaker="Boots">“Then I’ll hold this under it”</dialogue>, said the lad, and showed her the piece of broken plate.</p>
        <p><dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“You are so <descriptor speaker="Princess" subject="Boots" sign="negative">crooked</descriptor> in your words”</dialogue>
            , said the Princess, <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“there’s no knowing where to have you.”</dialogue></p>
        <p> <dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“No, I’m not crooked”</dialogue>, said the lad; <dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">
            “but this is”</dialogue>, as he held up one of the horns.</p>
        <p> <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“Well!”</dialogue> said the Princess, <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“I never saw the match of this in all my days.”</dialogue></p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“Why here you see the match to it”</dialogue>, said the lad, as he pulled out the other ram’s horn.</p>
        <p><dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“I think”</dialogue>, said the Princess, <dialogue speaker="Princess" subject="Boots">“you must have come here to wear out my tongue with your
            nonsense.”</dialogue></p> 
        <p><dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“No, I have not”</dialogue>, said the lad; <dialogue speaker="Boots" subject="Princess">“but this is worn out”</dialogue>, as he pulled out the
            shoe-sole. To this the Princess hadn’t a word to say, for she had fairly lost her voice
            with rage. <dialogue subject="Boots" speaker="Princess">“Now you are mine”</dialogue>, said the lad; and so he got the Princess to <action actor="Boots" subject="Princess" sign="positive">wife</action>, and
            half the kingdom.</p>
    </body>
</story>
